<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gentile craft. The second part Being a most merrie and pleasant historie, not altogether vnprofitable nor any way hurtfull: verie fit to passe away the tediousnesse of the long winter evenings. By T.D.</title>
            <title>Gentle craft. Part 2</title>
            <author>Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849777</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849777</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177918</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12363)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177918)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1269:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gentile craft. The second part Being a most merrie and pleasant historie, not altogether vnprofitable nor any way hurtfull: verie fit to passe away the tediousnesse of the long winter evenings. By T.D.</title>
                  <title>Gentle craft. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Deloney, Thomas, 1543?-1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Newly corrected and augmented.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Elizabeth Purslow, dwelling nere Christ Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.D. = Thomas Deloney.</note>
                  <note>Another edition of Deloney, Thomas.  The second part of, the gentle craft (STC 6555.7).</note>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Haud curo invidiam.</note>
                  <note>Chapter 6 begins on F3 verso and chapter 9 begins on I1 recto--STC.</note>
                  <note>Purslowe paid one pound for the use of the poor of the company on 9 April 1640 for permission to print this edition. See "Records of the Court of the Stationers' Company 1602 to 1640", p. 489--STC.</note>
                  <note>imperfect; cropped affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shoemakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GENTILE CRAFT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">The ſecond Part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being a moſt merrie and pleaſant Hiſtorie, not altogether vnprofitable nor any way hurtfull: verie fit to paſſe away the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſneſſe of the long winter evenings.</p>
            <p>By <hi rend="italic">T. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Newly corrected and augmented.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Haud curo invidam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi rend="italic">Elizabeth Purſlow,</hi> dwelling neere Chriſt Church 1639</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:3"/>
            <head>To the Maſter and Ward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> worſhipfull company of the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in London, all continuance of health and fect brotherly affection.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Nce more hath good will embolde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> me, to preſent vnto your Worſhips, my worthles labour, to manifeſt the good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection I beare to this fraternity: and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, you lent a gentle looke on the firſt part of this Hiſtory, I have beene the more bolde to proffer you the ſecond: for having bound my ſelfe by promiſe to performe it: and you perhaps clayming pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe as a debt, expecting payment, I bent all my ſtudy to keepe touch: whereupon I tender this ſmall trifle vnto you, onely crauing at your worſhips hands, a good opinion of my poore endevours. And albeit this pamphlet doth not miniſter matter worthy your grave view: yet in regard of the ſubject, I truſt you will deigne to eſteeme it ſith ſo well as I could, though not ſo well as I would, I have ſought herein to procure your delight: and although you finde not all the men ſpoken of, which is promiſed in the firſt part, yet thinke it no faintnes in me, but fault of good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: and againe, for as much as theſe men here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, were all of this Citie (whoſe ſtory grew longer then I ſuppoſed) and the other of the country: I thought good ſo to breake off, and to defer their ſtory to another time, when I may more perfectly ſpeake thereof. In the meane ſpace I commend your Worſhips to the protection of the moſt higheſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all he may. <hi rend="italic">T. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:4"/>
            <head>To the Courteous Readers health.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, you that vouchſafe to caſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous lookes into this rude Pamphlet: expect not herein to find any matter of light value, curiouſly pen'd with pickt words, or choiſe phraſes, but a quaint and plaine diſcourſe, beſt fitting matters of merriment, ſeeing wee have herein no cauſe to talke of Courtiers or Scholers. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtsnding, if you find your ſelfe over charged with me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, you may perhaps have here a fit medicine to purge that humour, by conferring in this place wich Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi rend="italic">Burket:</hi> or if you meet with round <hi rend="italic">Robin,</hi> he may chance ryme it away. I tell you among Shoomakers is ſome ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, as you ſhall ſee by Tom <hi rend="italic">Drums</hi> entertainment, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mad merry prankes playd by the Greene-King of S. Martins. If that will not ſuffice, you may in meeting with Anthony now now, have ſuch a fit of mirth, with his fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Fiddle, that it ſhall be a great cauſe to expell choler. And ſo I leave you to your owne liking, whether you will enter to ſee this ſport or no: ſtand backe I pray, roome for a Gentleman, for you cannot come in vnder a groat.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:4"/>
            <head>CHAP. 1. Containing the Hiſtory of Richard Caſteler: and the firſt of his love</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uely Maidens of the Citty of <hi rend="roman">Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> noting what a good a husband <hi rend="roman">Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Caſteler</hi> was and ſeéing how diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hée followed his buſineſſe, judged in the end hée would prove a rich man: for which cauſe many bore vnto him very good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; few there was that wiſhed not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be his wife: inſomuch that he hauing the cuſtome of all the pretty Wenches in the Citty, by that meanes knew the length of every Maidens foot ſo well, that he about all other beſt pleaſed them: On the Sundayes when he came into the Church, the Maides eyes were ſo firmely fired on him, that hée could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looke forward, backeward, nor on any ſide, but that he ſhould be ſure to haue a winke of one, a ſmile of another the third would give a nod: and to be briefe, they would all caſt on him ſuch gracious lookes, that it was eaſie to gueſſe by their outward countenance, their inward good will.</p>
            <p>And when in his Holy-dayes attire he paſt along the ſtréets, the Maidens (after their buſineſſe was done) ſtanding at their Maſters doores and ſpying him, would ſay thus one to another: Now verily there goes a proper civill young man, wiſe &amp; thrifty: yea ſuch a one as in time will prove wondrous weal hy, and without all doubt, will come to great credit &amp; preferment theſe and the like words would they vſe of him continually, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he had among them ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enerall good opinion, that as he ſtood a dayes at his cutting boord, he ſhould be ſure to haue twenty curſies made him in an houre, by Maidens that paſt up and downe: ſome would beſtow on him dainty
<pb facs="tcp:177918:5"/> ſweetnoſegayes, of the faireſt flowers they could find, and other ſome would bring him handkerchers of Cambrick, and divers ſuch like favours, well bew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aying their friendſhip towards him.</p>
            <p>But among many that ſecretly affected him, I will onely tell of twaine, becauſe aboue all the reſt, their merriments doe onely remaine in memorie, the one of them was called <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> of the ſpread-Eagle, but more commonly knowne by the name of long <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> of <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter:</hi> The other was a proper neat wench named <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> of the George, both of them as wily as they were witty, who among all the Maides in <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſed to be the beſt ſervants; having therefore good wages, they maintained themſelues gallantly, and therwithall ſo honeſtly, that no man could quip them with bad liuing, though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward it fell out otherwiſe, as in this hiſtorie you ſhall heare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> was a maiden borne in <hi rend="roman">Lancaſhire,</hi> in height and proportion of body, paſſing the ordinary ſtature of women, but there-withall very comely, and of amiable countenance, her ſtrength was agréeable to her ſtature and her courage as great as them both: ſhe was of a quicke capacitie, and pleaſant diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of a liberall heart, and ſuch a one as would be ſodainely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and ſoone pleaſed, being readier to revenge her wrongs by weapons, then by words: and therein did ſhée differ from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of other women, becauſe ſhée could not abide much brabling: and ſo hée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>full was ſhée of her behaviour in her yonger yéeres, that her good properties far excéeding her portion, ſhe was woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by divers, but would be won by none, for the man whom ſhée moſt loved, leaſt thought upon her. And albeit ſhée manifeſted her good will by divers meanes, yet did <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> little regard it, having his mind nothing bent vnto marriage, by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> grew into ſuch ſad conceits as changed her chery chéekes into a gréene wan countenance: in-ſomuch that euery one wondred to ſée her penſiuenes.</p>
            <p>At laſt it chanced that <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> having occaſion to go into <hi rend="roman">London,</hi> it was her good fortune to méet with <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> of the George, whom her miſtres had ſent thither to buy Comfets, and Carawayes, with divers other ſwéet meates, for that they had a banket beſpoken by divers gallant Courtiers, which that night
<pb facs="tcp:177918:5"/> poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to come thither: but ſo ſoone as <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> ſpied her, ſhe ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſaying: <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> now in good ſadnes welmet, (if thou béeſt met a maid) and ill met (quoth ſhée) not méeting ſo good a maid as my ſelfe: Tuſh ſaid <hi rend="roman">Margaret;</hi> it is good for vs to thinke well of our ſelves, for there is enough that think ill of vs: mary I defie them quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> that thinks ill of me, and I reſpect as little their ſpéech, as they do my profit. For a woman with a good life, feares no man with an evill tung: If you bee ſo hot quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> where the wind blows ſo cold, what will you be by that time ſupper is ready, where the fire will be as fierce as your choller is great? and miſtake mee not good <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> though I ſaid men think ill of vs, I meane not thereby that any goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſo blemiſh our good names, but I ſuppoſe they thinke not ſo wel of vs as they might do that doe not love vs ſo well as to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vs.</p>
            <p>Nay ſaid <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> if that be all, I am at a good point; for though my maiden-head be ſome what burdenſom to beare, yet I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kéepe it, then beſtow it on a bad husband: but though I ſay it, though I be but a poore wench, I have choiſe of huſbands en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough, and ſuch as I am aſſured in my conſcience, would both love me well, and kéepe me gallantly. Wherefore then doe you not marry quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret?</hi> in my opinion it is the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingſt life that may be, when a woman ſhall have her husband come home and ſpeake in this ſort vnto her. How now Wife? how doſt thou my ſwéet-heart? what wilt thou have? or what doſt thou la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke? and therewithall kindly embracing her, gives her a gentle kiſſe, ſaying: ſpeake my prettie mouſe, wilt thou have a cup of Claret-wine, White-wine, or Sacke to ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r? and then perhaps he carues vnto her the leg of a Capon, or the wing of a Chicken, and if there be one bit better then other, ſhée h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th the choiſe of it: And if ſhe chance to long for any thing by and by it is ſent for with all poſſible ſpéed, and nothing is thought too deare to doe her good At laſt having well refreſh themſelues ſhe ſets her ſiluer whiſtle to her mouth, and calles her maid to cleare the boord: then going to the fire, he ſets her on his knée, and wantonly ſtroking her cheeke, amourouſly bee chockes her under the chin, fetching many ſtealing foutches at her rubie lips,
<pb facs="tcp:177918:6"/> and ſo ſoone as he heares the Bell ring eight a clocke, he calles her to goe to bed with him. O how ſwéet doe theſe words ſound in a womans eares? But when they are once cloſe betwéene a paire of ſhéetes, O <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> then, then: why what of that quoth ſhe? Nay nothing ſaith <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> but they ſléep ſoundly all night. Truly quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> there be many wiues, but few that méete with ſuch kind huſbands: but ſéeing you aſke me why I marry not, in troth <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> I would tell thée, if I had time to ſtay: but I I feare I have ſtood too long pratling here already, and therefore farewell good <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> when I ſée thée againe, thou ſhalt know more of my mind.</p>
            <p>Nay <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> heare you quoth ſhe, go but a little way with me, and I will goe home with you as ſtraight as a line, for I haue nothing to buy but a ſcore of Quinces, and couple of Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and that ſhall be done in a trice: <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> was contented for her good companies ſake to ſtay a while, and as ſoone as <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> had made her market, they ſettled themſelues to goe homeward, where by the way <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> entred into this communication.</p>
            <p>You did euen now demand a queſtion of me, and very deſirous you were to know why I did not marry when I was ſo well offered: Truſt me <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> I take you to be my friend, which makes me the more willing to vnfold my fancy, being as well perſwaded of your ſecreſie as I am of your amity, and there-upon I am the more willing to make you copartner of my counſailes. Fire in ſtraw will not be hidden, and the flames of affection wil burſt for that length, though it be long kept vnder. And truth it is that I haue forſaken good matches, for <hi rend="roman">I</hi> might haue had Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi rend="roman">Cornelius</hi> of the Guard if <hi rend="roman">I</hi> would, who as you know is wealthy, and therwithall of very good conuerſation, yet there was one thing made me refuſe his kind offer: what was that quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret. I</hi> pray thée tell? Quoth ſhe, he loved not me ſo well but <hi rend="roman">I</hi> loued another tenne times better, and therefore it is not good for handes to joyne, where hearts agrée not. No <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> no, there is a youth in our ſtréet that nearer touches my heart and better pleaſes my mind, notwithſtanding he ſhall go name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for it is an old prouerb, two may kéep counſell if one be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Nay then quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> if you dare not truſt me tell no-further,
<pb facs="tcp:177918:6"/> notwithſtanding I have had credit in as great matters as yours, for many a man hath put his life in my hands, &amp; found no hurt thereby, and as many women have commited their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets to me, as men have ventured their bodies with me. Go to <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> you are diſpoſed to ieſt ſaid <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> but ſweare by thy Maidenhead that thou wilt never bewray my liking, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent me in my love, &amp; I will ſhew thée all: nay fie do not ſo quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> ſhew not all for ſhame, leaſt more ſée it then my ſelfe, for ſo may they bluſh at thy boldnes, and nothing commend thy modeſty: but it is happy that I have a maidenhead left to ſweare by: elſe I perceiue I ſhould know nothing of thée: no truſt me quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> for ſuch a one as cannot kéepe her Maidenhead, wil neuer kéep a ſecret, and that made <hi rend="roman">Katherine</hi> of the Crane to be ſuch a blab: but now <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> I will procéed to the matter. What doe you thinke by <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> of the Roſe, the wakeful cock of <hi rend="roman">Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> is that the man? there is no reaſon I ſhould thinke amiſſe of him that euery man commends: neuertheleſſe, he is no body in reſpect of riches, being but a yong houſekéeper of one yeares ſtanding, a man God wot vnacquainted with the worlds guiſe, and to ſpeake truth nothing comparable to Maſter <hi rend="roman">Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</hi> I will tell thée what quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> that man which néedeth neither to flatter with his friends, nor borrow of his neighbours, hath riche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſufficient: and hée is moſt poore that hath leaſt wit, by which arguments I am able to proove, that the Cock is as weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as he is wary, for he will ſure be beholding to no body, or to as few as he may, and it is al wayes to be noted that men of ſuch mindes doe never prove beggers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> hearing <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> ſo ſtoutly to take <hi rend="roman">Richards</hi> part, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by her vehement ſpéches the great affection ſhe bore to him, and finding that ſhe was ſick of her owne diſeaſe, <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> ſought means to remoue the cauſe of her griefe, &amp; thereby thruſt her ſelfe into the greater ſorrow: And the policy ſhe vſed moſt herein, was to ſpeak altogether in <hi rend="roman">Richards</hi> diſpraiſe, ſéeking thereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to diſlodge her love, and the more firmely to plant her owne, whereupon ſhe vttered her mind in this ſort.</p>
            <p>Well <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> ſéeing you beare ſo good an opinion of <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:177918:7"/> the Roſe, I would not for a buſhel of Angels ſéek to diſſwade you: but becauſe you requeſt my opinion how I like the man, in troth I will tell thée my mind without fraud or flattory: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> is a gentle young man, curteous and kind, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent about his buſineſſe, and wary in his dealings, which argues good husb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndry. Notwithſtanding, I like not theſe ouer coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous fellowes, of ſuch gréedy mindes, ſuch penny fathers, and pinchf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtes, that will not part from the paring of their nailes, nor the dropping of their noſe, if they thought it would yéeld them but the fourth part of a farthing. Tell me I pray thée what ioy ſhould a woman haue with ſuch a churle, that would grudge at every halfe-penny that is laid out that in a whole yeare would not leaue a farthing worth of muſtard vnwritten in his booke: And ſuch a one I feare will this Cocke prove, for me thinkes hée lookes with a hungry noſe, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wſoeuer you think of him, I know not, but I verily feare though hee be a Cocke by name, hée will never prove a Cock of the game. Againe he is but a dwarfe in reſpect of a man, a ſhrimpe, a Wren, a hop of my thumbe, ſuch a one as a body might hide in a wrinkle of their buttocks.</p>
            <p>Well <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> quoth ſhée, you are priuiledged to ſpeake your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but ſhould another thus miſtearme him, I would teare her face: I tell thée true I had rather haue a winner then a waſter, a ſparer then a prodigall ſpender: for when a man in his youth, hath gotten ſomething with paine, he may the better ſpend it in his age with pleaſure, and farre better it is hée ſhould be thought couetous, then careleſſe; his ſtature and proportion of body plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes me well enough, for it is no matter how great hée is, but how good hee is.</p>
            <p>But <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> ſéeing our talk hath indured ſo long, that it hath brought vs both home, let vs at our parting be mindfull of our promiſes, to kéepe ſecret whatſoeuer hath been ſaid, for little knowes the young man the depth of my mind, and therefore would I kéepe it cloſe, till I ſaw ſome ſigne of good will procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from him, for it becommeth not maidens to be woers, though willingly they could wiſh to wed where they beſt fancie, and ſo farewell ſwéet <hi rend="roman">Margaret.</hi> Adue gentle <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> quoth <hi rend="roman">Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet,</hi> vntill our next méeting, when I hope I ſhall further vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:177918:7"/> of your procéedings in your loue.</p>
            <p>When <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> had thus vnderſtood her mind, and ſaw how ſhe matter went, ſhe ſought all meanes poſſible to preuenther, as hereafter ſhall be ſhewen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 2. How Margaret requeſted Richard to the eating of a Poſſet at night: And how her Maſters buttocks was ſcalded therewith.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T chanced that againſt Whitſontide, <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> ſtood in néed of a new paire of Shooes: Therefore in a morning betimes ſhe came to <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> of the Roſe to beſpeake them aforehand, and the more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare her kindnes, and to win his good will, ſhe carried with her a bottle of excellent good Muſkadine, which one of the Yeomen of the Kings wine ſeller had beſtowed upon her: and to make it reliſh the better, ſhe carried with her a dainty péece of powdred béefe, and the tender carkaſſe of a cold Capon, and thus pleſantly began to gréet him. All health to the kind cocke of <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter,</hi> that with the Larke gréetes the Sun riſing with a chéerefull note, and mounts aboue many to the loue of pretty laſſes. Tell me quoth ſhe thou bouny Lad, wilt thou take the length of my foote, and make me a good payre of ſhooes againſt Sunday? that I will <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> quoth he, therefore let me ſée thy foote: there is both my foote and leg ſaid <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> I am not aſhamed to ſhew either of them, for I am not legged like a Crane, nor footed like a Flie, and therewith lift up her cloathes to the knée, whereat <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> ſmiling ſaid; a little higher <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> and ſhew all: whereupon ſhe ſodainly replied in this ſort: ſoft <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> not ſo, for I will tell thée one thing.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Euery Carter may reach to the garter,</l>
               <l>A Shoomaker he may reach to the knee,</l>
               <l>But he that creepes higher ſhall aske leaue of me.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:8"/>
            <p>Good reaſon quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> leaue is light, which being obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a man may be bold without offence, but this onely is my griefe. I haue neuer a Laſt in my ſhop long enough for thy foot: then I would they were all fired quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg.</hi> He that will be counted a good workman muſt haue fooles to fit all perſons and I muſe that you which ſtrive to be counted excellent, will want neceſſaries: Fie <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> fie, thou ſhouldeſt neuer be vnprouided eſpecially for women.</p>
            <p>Well <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> quoth he, be contented, conſider you are a woman of no ordinary making, but as in height thou ouerlookeſt all, ſo in the length of thy foot thou ſurpaſſeſt all; therefore I muſt haue a paire of Laſts made for the nonce, and that ſhall be done out of hand: I tell thee <hi rend="roman">Dicke</hi> quoth ſhée, as high as I am, I am not ſo high as <hi rend="roman">Paules</hi> nor is my foot ſo long as Graus-end Barge. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> a paire of Laſts to fit thy foot will coſt as much as a hundred of fagots which will not be bought vnder ten groats: if they coſt a crown quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> let me haue them; what man rather then <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will goe without ſhooes I will beare the charge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reof my ſelfe and in token that I mean troth, take there the money, thou ſhalt find me no Crinkler, but one that will reward cunning to the vttermoſt: I loue not to pinch for a peny, or ſtand upon tearmes for two pence, if I find my ſhooes good I will not ſhrinke for a ſhilling; In troth quoth <hi rend="roman">Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> franke cuſtomers are worthy of good ware, and therefore <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> doubt not, for thou ſhalt haue as good a ſhoe as euer was drawne upon womans foote, God a mercy for that ſweet <hi rend="roman">Dicke</hi> quoth ſhee, and ſéeing thou ſaiſt ſo, I will beſtow this bottle of wine on thee to breakfaſt, beſide that, I haue brought here a modſcome that will proue as good a ſhooing-horne to drawe downe a cup of Muſkadine as may be: and therewithall ſhee pluckt out her powdred beefe and her colde Capon; <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> ſeeing this, with thankes to <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> for her meat, reacht out a couple of ioyne ſtooles, and after that they had laid a cloth thereon, they downe did ſit, at which time many merry ſpéeches did paſſe betwéene them. And at that very time there was in the ſame ſhoppe, amongſt a great many other men a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
<pb facs="tcp:177918:8"/> iorney man called round <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> being a wel truſt fellow ſhort and thicke, yet very actiue and pleaſantly conceited: for ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hée was held in high reputation among all the Shoomakers in <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter,</hi> and he would ſcant ſpeake any thing but in rime. This iolly companion ſéeing them bent ſo well to their breakfaſt, and nothing at all to reſpect him, in the place where he ſate caſt out theſe merry ſpéeches vnto them.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Much good doe it you maſters and well may you fare,</l>
               <l>Beſhroe both your hearts and if you do ſpare:</l>
               <l>The wine ſhould be nought as I judge by the ſmell,</l>
               <l>And by the colour too I know it full well.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Nay faith quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> that's but a ieſt,</l>
            </q>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Ile ſweare quoth Robin tis none of the beſt.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Taſt it quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> then tell me thy mind:</l>
            </q>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Yea marry quoth Robin now you are kind.</l>
            </q>
            <p>With that <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> filling a cup brim full, gaue it into his hand ſaying: Now taſt it <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> and take there the cup. <hi rend="roman">Nay hang me quoth Robin if I drinke it not up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By my Maiden-head quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> I ſée that thou art a good fellow: and to haue thée drinke it up, is the thing that I craue.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Then ſweare quoth Robin by the thing you haue,</l>
               <l>For this to ſweare I dare be bold:</l>
               <l>You were a maid at three yeares old.</l>
               <l>From three to foure, five, ſixe, and ſeaven,</l>
               <l>But when you grew to be eleuen,</l>
               <l>Then you began to breed deſire;</l>
               <l>By twelue your fancy was on fire:</l>
               <l>At thirteene yeares deſire grew quicke,</l>
               <l>And then your maiden-head fell ſicke:</l>
               <l>But when you came vnto fourteene,</l>
               <l>All ſecret kiſſes was not ſeene:</l>
               <l>By that time fifteene yeares was paſt,</l>
               <l>I gueſſe your maiden-head was loſt.</l>
               <l>And I pray God forgiue me this,</l>
               <l>If thinking ſo I thinke amiſſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now by my honeſty quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> you doe me mighty wrong to
<pb facs="tcp:177918:9"/> thinke ſo ill of me: for though indéed I confeſſe, I cannot excuſe my ſelfe, for women are not Angels, though they haue Angels aces: for to ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake the truth might I haue had my owne hearts deſire when time was, I would rather haue choſen to lye with a man then a maid, but ſuch merry motions were out of my mind many a déere day agoe, and now I vow that a maiden I will die.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>By this wine quoth Robin I dare ſweare you lye,</l>
               <l>For were I as my maſter by this good light,</l>
               <l>You would leeſe your maiden head ere twelve a clock at night.</l>
               <l>With high derry derry,</l>
               <l>If it be not gone already.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Nay quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> your Maſter ſcornes me, he kéeps all his gownes for <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> of the George: a pretty wench I confeſſe, hauing a proper body but a bad leg, ſhe hath a very good counteance but an ill coulour, and you talk of deſire, but her deſire I doubt will bring her the gréene ſickneſſe, if your maſter like a good Phiſition giue her not a medicine againſt that malady: why <hi rend="roman">Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> hath ſhe told you ſo much of her mind, that you know her griefe ſo well? It may be ſhe hath quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> but whether ſhe did or no, it is ſufficient that I know ſo much: But I thinke quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> you are not ſo beſotted to make any account of a Tallow cake.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>No faith quoth Robin, a nut-browne girle,</l>
               <l>Is in mine eye a Diamond and a Pearle:</l>
               <l>And ſhee that hath her cheekes cherry red,</l>
               <l>Is euer beſt welcome to a young mans bed.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Certainly quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> which is the beſt or worſt I know not yet, nor doe I meane haſtily to prove; and as <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> of the George, as ſhe hath no reaſon to hate me, ſo ſhe hath no cauſe to loue me: but if ſhe doe, it is more favour then I did euer merit at her hand, and ſurely were it but in regard of her good will, I am not to ſcorne her nor for her favour to féed her with floutes, but for her good thoughts of me to think well of her, though not ſo well as to make her my wife: Well ſaid Maſter, quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>In this ſort grind you ſtill,</l>
               <l>So ſhall we haue mo ſackes to mill.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Truſt me quoth <hi>Margaret,</hi> I ſpeake not this ſo much to diſgrace
<pb facs="tcp:177918:9"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> as for the regard I haue to your credit: but to make an end of <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> and this ieſt altogether, let me entreat you ſoone at night to come to our houſe; and thinke this, though your chéere chance to be ſmall your welcome ſhall be great. I know that this Summer (and eſpecially againſt theſe holy-daies) you will worke till ten, and I promiſe you by eleuen I will haue as good a poſſet for you, as euer you did taſte on in your life. My maſter is an old man, and he commonly goes to bed at nine, and as for my miſtris, I know where ſhe will be ſafe till midnight maſſe be ended, ſo that for an houre we may be as merry as pope <hi rend="roman">Iohn:</hi> what ſay you <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> quoth ſhe, will you come? In troth <hi rend="roman">Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> quoth he, I heartily thank you for your good will, I would willingly come but I loue not to be from home ſo late.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>I thinke ſo quoth Robin leaſt you ſhould miſſe Kate,</l>
               <l>But take my counſell, when you are with Meg:</l>
               <l>Suppoſe you haue got fine Kate by the leg.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> ſaid he, thou art ſo full of thy rime, that often thou, art without reaſon; thou ſéeſt that <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> hath béen at coſt with vs to day, and it is more then good manners to charge her further, before we haue made amends for this: and beſide that late walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the euening brings young men into much ſuſpition. Tuſh quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> once and vſe it not, is not ſuch a matter: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſwéet <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> you ſhall come, and you ſhall not ſay me nay, therefore <hi rend="roman">I</hi> charge you on paine of diſpleaſure not to faile, and forget not to bring round <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> with you, and ſo farewell.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>No faith quoth Robin, it ſhall not need,</l>
               <l>I am bidden already and ſo God ſpeed.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Who bad thee quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret?</hi>
            </p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>What are thy wits ſo vnſteady?</l>
               <l>You did bid me quoth Robin, haue you forgot already?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Why then I pray thée good <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> ſaid <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> do not forget in any caſe, and put thy Maſter in mind thereof if he ſhould chance to change his opinion, or ouerſlip the time through gréedines of work for I faith <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> if thou bring him along with thée, I will thinke the better of thée while <hi rend="roman">I</hi> liue: why then quoth he.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>And as I am no knight,</l>
               <l>We will come to eate the poſſet ſoone at night.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:10"/>
            <p>Now <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> was no ſooner gone, and <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> at his cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting boord, and <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> ſet on his ſtoole, but in comes <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> of the George, bringing in her aporne the corner of a Veniſon Paſtie, and a good deale of a Lambe pye, who with a ſmyling countenance entring the ſhop, bidding <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> good morrow, askt if he had broke his faſt? yes verily quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> I thank long <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> we haue béene at it this morning, and had you come a little ſooner you had found her héere, for ſhe went away but euen now, and <hi rend="roman">I</hi> verily thinke ſhe is ſcant at home yet.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Tis a luſty wench quoth Robin gentle and kind,</l>
               <l>And in truth ſhe beares a moſt bountifull mind.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> hearing <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> to enter into <hi rend="roman">Megs</hi> commendations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to grow iealous of the matter: out upon her foule ſtammell quoth ſhe, he that takes her to his wife ſhall be ſure of fleſh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough, let him get bread where he can: tis ſuch a bold betrice, ſhe will acquaint her ſelfe with euery bodie. Notwithſtanding this I will tell you <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> the leſſe ſhe comes in your company, the more it will befor your credit. And howſoever ſhee deſerues it, God knowes, I cannot accuſe her, but I promiſe you ſhe hath but a hard report among many. But letting her reſt as ſhe is, ſée here what I haue brought you, and with that ſhe gaue him the Veniſon and the reſt, and drawing her purſe, ſhe would needs ſend for a quart of wine, <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> ſought to perſwade her to the contrary, but ſhe would not be intreated; what man quoth ſhe, I am able to giue you a quart of wine. That's ſpoke like an Angell quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>And this I doe thinke,</l>
               <l>If you be able to giue it, we be able to drinke.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Hereupon the wine was fetcht, and ſo they ſate them downe to their meate, at what time they fed not ſo heartily on the Veniſon paſty, but <hi rend="roman">Gillians</hi> eye fed as gréedily on <hi rend="roman">Richards</hi> faour: &amp; as ſoone as the wine was come, ſhe plucktout of her pocket a good péece of ſugar, &amp; filling a glaſſe of wine tempered wel therwith, ſhe drank to him ſaying: here <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> to all that loue you and me, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to him whom <hi rend="roman">I</hi> loue beſt: let it come quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> I will pledge him whoſoeuer it be.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>So will I quoth Robin without any faile,</l>
               <l>Were it the beſt Hipocras, I would turn it ouer my naile.</l>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:10"/>
            <p>Then <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> looking round about ſpoke to this effect: verily <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> héere is a pretty houſe, and every thing hanſome by Saint <hi rend="roman">Anne,</hi> I ſée nothing wanting but a good wiſe to kéep all things in his due kind: whereunto <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> made this anſwer.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Now ſpeake thy conſcience, and tell me good Gill,</l>
               <l>Wouldſt not thou be that good wife, with a good will?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Who I? alas quoth ſhe, your Maſter ſcornes me, he looks for a golden girle, or a girle with gold, that might bring him the red ruddocks thinking in a bag, and yet poſſible he were better to have one with leſſe money, and more huswifery: for my owne part I thanke God, and in a good time may I ſpeake it, I would not come to learne of never a woman in <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter,</hi> how to deale in ſuch affaires: I thinke no leſſe quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray God ſend you a good husband, and one well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo good a wife: with that <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> fetcht a great ſigh, ſaying; Amen I pray God, for it is a ſinfull thing to leade a ſinfull life, except: Nay, ſay your mind, ſpeake your mind quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard:</hi> Why quoth ſhe? it is written, that we ſhall giue an account for every idle word, and that ill thoughts are as bad as wanton déeds: it is true quoth <hi rend="roman">Rich rd,</hi> then God helpe vs all quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> but if I were married, I ſhould remove a great many of them. Why then marry me quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> and thereby prevent the perill of bad thoughts: harke in thy eare <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> quoth ſhe, I would thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter would ſay as much and then he ſhould ſoone know my mind.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Ha, ha, quoth Robin, I faith you drab,</l>
               <l>And would you have him to ſtampe the crab?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Why what is the matter quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard?</hi> nay nothing quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> but that I was bold to jeſt with your man, and I hope you will not be offended if he and I talke a word or two. There is no reaſon I ſhould quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> and therefore conferre at your pleaſure, and the whileſt I will be buſie with the Lambe pye, then <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> rounding <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> in the eare, ſpoke in this ſort vnto him. I perceiue you can ſpie day at a little hole: you may ſée <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> love is like an vnruly ſtreame that will over-flow the banks if the courſe be once ſtopt, as by my ſpéeches no doubt you have noted: neuertheleſſe how forcible ſoeuer fancy is, it is thought ſmall modeſty in a maiden to lay open her heart in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:177918:11"/> caſes, but I am of opinion that affection growing as ſtrong in a woman as a man, they ought to haue equall priv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ledge, as well as men to ſpeake their minds. <hi rend="roman">Robi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> I take thee to be an honeſt fellow, and it is the part of a man in caſes of honeſt love to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt poore maidens: counſell the key of certainty, which makes me to require bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h thy counſaile and help In truth <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laine, I love thy Maſter with all my heart: and if thou wouldſt be ſo much my friend to break the matter vnto him and therewithall to procure his good liking to me, I would beſtow on thée as good a ſute of apparell as euer thou waſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter of in thy life: wherevnto <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> anſwered, ſaying,
<q rend="roman">
                  <l>Heer's my hand Gillian, at thy requeſt</l>
                  <l>Ile make a vow Ile doe my beſt,</l>
                  <l>But for my apparell grant me this,</l>
                  <l>In earneſt firſt to give me a kiſſe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>There it is quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> and I doe proteſt, that upon that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed day, when h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gives his happy conſent to be my husband, at the deliuery of thy apparell <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will make that one kiſſe twenty, and hereupon ſhaking hands, they came to the tabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſet them downe againe. <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> marking all, ſaid nothing, but at her approach to the boord tooke the glaſſe and drunk to her, giuing her thankes for her coſt and kindnes: ſhe gladly accepting the ſame, bending her body in ſtead of curſie, tooke it at his hands, and with a winke drunk vnto <hi rend="roman">Robi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and ſo taking her leave of them both as light as a Doe ſhe ran ſpéedily ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>So ſoone as ſhe was gone, <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> told his Maſter it was the pleaſanteſt life in the world to live a Batcheler, during which time he could neither want good chéere nor good comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny: I ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> but what I get one way I ſpend another way, while I paſſe the time in trifling about nothing: you ſée quoth he, here is a forenoone ſpent to no purpoſe, and all by the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ans of a couple of giglets, that haue greater deſire to be playing with a man, then to be mindfull to follow their buſines: but if I liue I will ſodainly avoid both their delights and their loues. I tell thee <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> I account their favours full of frawd, and their intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments daungerous, and therefore a man muſt not be won with faire words as a fiſh with a baite.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:11"/>
            <p>Well Maſter quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> all is one to me, whether you love them or loath, but yet ſoone at night let not the poſſet be for got.</p>
            <p>Beleeve me quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> if I reſt in the mind I am in now, I meane not to be there at all. O then you will looſe her love, quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> for euer and euer Amen: that, ſaid his Maſter is the onely thing that I requeſt, for the love of a ſhroe is like the ſhadow of a cloude that conſumeth as ſoone as it is ſéene, and ſuch love had I rather looſe then find.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>But yet quoth <hi>Robin,</hi> this once follow my mind</l>
               <l>Though by her love you ſet but light,</l>
               <l>Let vs eate the poſſet ſoone at night:</l>
               <l>And afterward I will ſo deale,</l>
               <l>If you will not my trickes reveale:</l>
               <l>That they ſhall trouble you no more,</l>
               <l>Though by your love they ſet great ſtore:</l>
               <l>For one another they ſhall beguile,</l>
               <l>Yet thinke themſelves well pleas'd the while.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Verily quoth his Maſter, if thou wilt doe ſo, I wil be <hi rend="roman">Megs</hi> gueſt for this once, and happy ſhall I thinke my ſelf to be ſo well rid of them: Hereupon being reſolved, they plyde their worke hard till the euening, and when the Sunne was crept under the earth, and the Stars up in the skies, <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> having his ſhop window ſhut in and his doores made faſt, he with his man <hi rend="roman">Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> tooke their direct way to the ſpread Eagle, where they no ſooner knockt at the doore, but <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> came downe and let them in, with ſuch a chéerefull countenance, as gave perfect teſtimony of their welcome. Now <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> quoth ſhe, I will witneſſe you are a man of your word, and a man that hath a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his promiſe: I pray you hartily come néere, for to have you come in my office, is my deſire: but tell vs firſt quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> was your office never a fire? Y faith no quoth ſhe, you ſée the kitchin is large and the chimney wide: but how many rookes quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> hath the goodnes of your kitchin tride? I know not ſaid <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> how many or how few: truſt me quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> I thinke euen ſo. Goe to quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> I ſmell out your knauery, and gueſſe at your meaning, but taking it to be ſpoken more for mirth, then for malice, I let them paſſe. Then taking <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:177918:12"/> the hand, ſhe had him ſit downe ſaying, good <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> think your ſelfe welcome, for in froth I have neuer a friend in the world that can be better welcome: I thank you good <hi rend="roman">Magaret</hi> ſaid he.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>I thank her ſtill quoth <hi rend="italic">Robin,</hi> with thanks of every degree,</l>
               <l>For you that have all the welcome, ſhall give all thanks for mee,</l>
            </q>
            <p>Why <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> q. <hi>Meg,</hi> be not offended for thou art welcome to mee,
<q rend="roman">I faith quoth he, you bid me welcome when you haue nothing elſe to do.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Herewithall <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> very neately laying the cloth, with all things neceſſary, ſet a dainty minſt pie on the boord piping hote, with a great deale of other good chéere, and having ſent another maid of the houſe for a pottle of wine, they fell to their meat mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, whereof when they had eaten and drunk, <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> ſtepping from the boord went to reach the poſſet, but while ſhe had it in her hands ſhe ſodainly heard one comming down the ſtairs: Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious quoth ſhe, my Maſtercomes, what ſhift ſhall we make to hide the poſſet, if he chance to ſée it, we ſhall have more anger then ten poſſets are worth with that ſhe quickly whipt into ſhe yard, and ſet the poſſet downe upon the ſeat in the privy-houſe, thinking it there ſafeſt out of ſight, for her Maſter being an old crabbed fellow, would often ſteale downe to ſée what his maids were a doing, but God wot that was not the cauſe; for the old man being raiſed by the looſenes of his body, came haſtily downe to pay tribute to <hi rend="roman">Aiax,</hi> where when he was come, he clapt his buttocks into the poſſet, where with being grieuouſly ſcalded, he cried out ſaying, alacke, alacke, help maids, help, or I am ſpoild for euer; for ſome ſpirit or divell in the foule bottome of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie hath throwne up boyling leade upon my buttocks and in this caſe like one dauncing the trench more he ſtampt up and downe the yard, holding his hips in his hands: <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> that better knew what the matter was then her maſter, ran into the houſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice with a ſpit in her hand, as if ſhe had béene purpoſed to broch the divell, and there caſting the well ſpiced poſſet into the midſt of the puddle taking the baſon away, ſaid, how now Maſter, what is the matter, who hath hurt you, or are you not hurt at all? Hurt quoth her maſter, I fell thee <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> neuer was man thus hurt, and yet I am aſhamed to ſhew my hurt: bring
<pb facs="tcp:177918:12"/> me a Candle quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> I tell you Maſter, it is better all ſhould be ſhewen, then all ſhould be ſpoyled: and there with ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting by his ſhirt, ſpied both his great chéekes full of ſmall bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whereupon ſhe was faine with all poſſible ſpéed to make him a medicine with ſallet oyle and houſeléeks, to aſſwage the fury of an vnſéene fire. And by meanes of this vnhappy chance, <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> with his man was faine ſecretly to ſlip away, and to goe home without taſting the poſſet at all: which was to <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> no ſmall griefe, and yet they could both of them ſcant ſtand for laughing, to thinke how odly this, leaſt fell out.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>I am quoth <hi rend="italic">Robin,</hi> forty yeares old and more,</l>
               <l>Yet did I never know poſſet, ſo taſted before:</l>
               <l>I thinke his eyes in his Elbowes he had,</l>
               <l>To thruſt his arſe in the poſſet, or elſe he was mad.</l>
            </q>
            <p>His maſter anſwering ſaid, beleeue me <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> I neuer knew ſhe like in my life, but by the grace of God I will neuer goe there no more to eate a poſſet: and ſo going to bed they ſlept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſorrow till morning. At what time <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> comming thither told them ſhe was very ſorie they were ſo ſuddenly broke from their banket; but Y faith <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> (quoth ſhe) another time ſhall make amends for all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 3. How the Cocke of Weſtminſter was married to a Dutch mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, for which cauſe Long <hi rend="italic">Meg,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gillian</hi> of the George, wore willow Garlands.</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ichard Caſteler</hi> liuing a long time a Batchelor in <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter,</hi> after many good proffers made vnto him, refuſing all hee at laſt linked his loue to a young Dutch maiden dwelling in <hi rend="roman">London,</hi> who beſides that, was of proper perſonage, and comely countenance, and could doe diuers pretty feates to get her owne living To this pretty ſoule went <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> ſecretly a wooing, who for halfe a yeare ſet as light by him, as hée did by the Maidens of <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter,</hi> And the more hée was denyed, the more deſirous is hee was to ſeeke her good will, much like to an vnruly patient, that moſt longes after the meate hee is moſt forbidden:
<pb facs="tcp:177918:13"/> and ſuch is the fury of fond Lovers, to eſtéeme them moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, that are to them moſt pernitious: he ſcornfully ſhunnes ſuch as gently ſéekes him, and wooes her earneſtly that ſhakes him off frowardly: but while he was thus buſied to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe bleſſed by matching with a Mayden in <hi rend="roman">London,</hi> round <hi rend="roman">Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> caſt in his mind how to ſet the Maydens wittes a worke in <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter,</hi> which he effected as occaſion was offred in this ſort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> comming often by the ſhop, caſt many a ſhéepes eye to ſpye out their beloued friend, and after they had many times miſt him from his buſines, they thought either that he was growne love-ſick or lazie: but knowing him a man to be mightily addicted to the getting of money, judged that it was not idlenes, that withdrew him from his buſines, but rather that he was gone a wooing to one pretty wench or other, for loving hearts have euer ſuſpicious heades and iealouſie is copart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with affection: whereupon <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> entred into theſe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with round <hi rend="roman">Robin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſe much quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> where pour Maſter layes his knife a boord now adayes, for ſeldome or never can I ſée him in his ſhop: truſt me, I doubt, he is become thriftles, and will prove but a bad husband in the end: tell me <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> ſaid ſhe, I pray thee ſay where doth the Cocke crow now?</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Not ſo ſaid <hi rend="italic">Robin,</hi> my Maſter will not that allow,</l>
               <l>I muſt not ſhew his ſecrets to one or other:</l>
               <l>Therefore you ſhall not know it though you were my mother,</l>
               <l>Yet thus much by thy ſpeech I plainly do ſee,</l>
               <l>Thou thinkſt not ſo well of him as he thinks on thee.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> hearing round <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> rime to ſo good purpoſe, asked if hee knew his Maſters minde ſo much? truly, quoth ſhée, if I wiſt he bore any ſpark of love toward me, it ſhould neither goe vnregarded nor vnrewarded, therefore ſwéet <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> let me know whereupon thou ſpeakeſt; feare not my ſecrecie, for I will rather looſe my life then bewray his love. Héereupon <hi rend="roman">Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> ſaid, that his Maſter was very well affected towards her, and that if it were not that <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> of the George did caſt ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eyes into his actions, he would long ere this h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve vttred his mind: but quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> he is ſo haunted by that female ſpirit,
<pb facs="tcp:177918:13"/> that he can take no reſt in no place for her, and therefore the more to quiet his mind, he hath left his ſhop to my charg, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken himſelfe to wander the Woods ſo wild.</p>
            <p>Theſe words vttered by <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> made <hi rend="roman">Margarets</hi> heart leape in her belly: wherefore taking gently her leave of him, ſhe thus began to meditate on the maſter: Now doe I well ſée that the tongue of a wiſe man is in his heart, but the heart of a foole is in his tongue: and <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> quo h ſhe, haſt thou borne me ſuch ſecret good will and would neuer let me know it? Iwis, Iwis, ſoone would thy ſorrow be aſſwaged if thou ſoughteſt remedie at my hand: well though the fire be long ſuppreſt, at length it will burſt into a flame and <hi rend="roman">Richards</hi> ſecret good will, at laſt will ſhew it ſelfe, till when I will reſt my ſelfe conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, thinking it ſufficient that I know he loves me: and ſéeing it is ſo, I will make him ſue and ſerve, and daunce atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance after me: when he is moſt curteous, I will be moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y, and as it were ſcorning his proffers, and ſhunning his preſence, I will make him the more earneſt to intreat my favour: when he ſayes he loves me, <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will laugh at him, and ſay he canfaine and flatter well: if he affirme he be grieued through my diſdaine, and that the lacke of my good wil hath béen his greateſt ſorrow, I will ſay alas good ſoule, how long have you béen love-ſick? pluck out thy heart man and be of good chéere, there is more maids then Malkin: though I doe lightly eſtéeme thee there are ſome that perhaps will better regard both thy griefe, and thy good will: and therefore good <hi rend="roman">Dicke</hi> trouble me no more.</p>
            <p>Thus muſt maides diſſemble leaſt they be counted too curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſhewing themſelvs ouer fond, become the leſſe favoured, for a womans love being hardly obtained, is eſtéemed moſt ſwéet, therefore we muſt giue our lovers an hundred denials for faſhion ſake, though at the firſt we could find in our hearts to accept their proffered pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Thus in a jolly humor <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> letted home, flattering her ſelfe in her happy fortune, in which delight we will leave her, and make ſome rehearſall of <hi rend="roman">Gillians</hi> ioy: who comming in the like manner to <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> asking for his Maſter, was certified by him, that for her ſake onely he lived in ſuch ſorrow, that he
<pb facs="tcp:177918:14"/> could not ſtay in his ſhop, and therfore was faine to driue away melancholy by marching abroad. O <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> (quoth he) had it not bin for two cauſes, he would long ere this haue vttered his mind vnto thée, for he loues thée aboue meaſure: Y faith, quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> is it true <hi rend="roman">(Robin)</hi> that thou doſt tell me? Doubt not of that (quoth he) doe you think that I will tell you a lye? I ſhould gaine nothing by that I am ſure: if then you will beléeue me you may, if not chuſe, I meane not to intreat you there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o: Nay good <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> (quoth ſhe) be not angry, though I credit thy ſpéeches, yet blame me not to aske a queſtion, aske what you will quoth <hi rend="roman">Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> I reſpect it not, and I may chuſe whether I will anſwere you or no: Swounds, now I haue opened my maſters ſecret, you were beſt blab it through all the towne. Nay good <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> that is not my mind quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> but I beſéech thée, let me know thoſe two cauſes that kéepes thy Maſter from vttering his mind: Nay ſoft, there lay a ſtraw for feare of ſtumbling quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> hold your peace <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> it is not good to eate too much hony, nor to gorge you with too much gladnes: let it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that you know what you know. Nay good ſwéet <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> quoth ſhe, I pray thée make it not dainty now to tell me all, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you haue begun: the day may come that I may requite thy curteſie to the full: Say you ſo, <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> quoth hée? now by good <hi rend="roman">Criſpianus</hi> ſoule I ſweare, were it not that I am in hope you will prove kind to my Maſter, and be a good Miſtreſſe to vs when you are married, I would not vtter one word more, no not halfe a word, nor one ſillable. Well <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> quoth ſhe if euer I come to command in thy maſters houſe, and to carry the keys of his Cubberts gingling at my ſides, thou ſhalt ſée I will not kéepe a niggards Table, to haue bare platters brought from the boord, but you ſhall haue meate and drinke plenty, and be vſed as men ought to be vſed in all reaſonable manner. And whereas you ſéeme to make doubt of my kindneſſe toward thy Maſter ha <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> I would thou kneweſt my heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> hearing this, told her this tale, that his maſter loved her intyrely, and would long ſince haue vttered his mind, but for two reaſons: the firſt was, that he could never find fit opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to doe it, becauſe of Long <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> whoſe loue to him was
<pb facs="tcp:177918:14"/> more then he could wiſh, and ſuch as he would gladly remove if he might: for ſaith <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> though my Maſter do not care a ſtraw for her, yet ſhe caſts ſuch a vigilant eye upon him, that if he do but ſpeake, or looke upon any, ſhe by and by poutes and lowres, and many times inveyes againſt the parties with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull termes, which is to my Maſter ſuch a griefe, that he is faine to kéepe ſilent, what otherwiſe ſhould be ſhown: and the ſecond reaſon is this, that becauſe he is not ſo wealthy as he could wiſh himſelfe, you would diſdaine his ſute, and make no account of his good will. Who I quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian?</hi> now by theſe ten bones it was never my mind to ſay him nay. I tell thée <hi rend="roman">Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> I doe more reſpect his kindnes then his goods: he is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per youth and well conditioned, and it is far better to have a man without money, then money without a man. Why then good <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> harken hither thrée dayes hence, and you ſhall heare more, but in the meane ſpace looke you play mum budget, and ſpeake not a word of this matter to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I warrant thée <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> quoth ſhe, and ſo away ſhe went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as glad of this tydings as her Maſter was of a good Term: Now when his Maſter came home, his man <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> asked him how he ſped in his ſuit? verily quoth he, even as Cookes doe in baking of their pies, ſometimes well, ſometimes ill. <hi rend="roman">London</hi> Maids are wily wenches: on Sunday my ſwéet-heart was halfe won, but now I doubt ſhe is wholy loſt. Now ſhe is in one mind, by and by in another, and to be briefe never ſtedfaſt in any thing.</p>
            <p>Tuſh Maſter quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> ſtoop not too much to a thiſtle, but take this comfort, that what one will not another will: I tel you Maſter, Crabs yéeldes nothing but ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>juice, a ſower ſauce good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or digeſtion but bad to the taſte, and theſe nice minions are ſo full of curioſity, that they are cleane without curteſie: Yet well fare the gallant girles of <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter,</hi> that will doe more for a man then he will doe for himſelfe. What is that ſaid his Maſter? mary quoth he, get him a wife ere he is aware, and give two kiſſes before he calles for one. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t indéed is extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary kindnes quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> but their loves are like brai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed wares, which are often ſhowne, but hardly ſold.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:15"/>
            <p>Well Maſter quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> you know your two old friends <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Gillian:</hi> I, what of them quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard?</hi> Introth quoth he, I have made them both ſo proud, that they pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce through the ſtréets like the Kings great horſes: for I have made them both beléeue that you love them out of all cry. And I beſhroe thy heart for that quoſh <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> for therein thou doſt both d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceive them, and diſcredit mée: I aſſure thée I like not ſuch je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Now gip quoth Robin are you griev'd at my talke?</l>
               <l>And if you be angry I pray you goe walke.</l>
               <l>Thus you doe never eſteeme of a man,</l>
               <l>Let him doe for you the beſt that he can.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> hearing his man ſo hot, pacified him with many cold and gentle ſpéeches, wiſhing if he had begun any jeſt, that he ſhould finiſh it with ſuch diſcretion, that no reproach might grow thereby unto him, and then he would be content: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> procéeded in this ſort.</p>
            <p>Vpon a time <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> according to her wonted manner came thither, whom <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> perſwaded that his Maſter was newly gone into Tuttle field, and that he left word if ſhe came ſhe ſhould doe ſo much as to méet him there: but quoth he, take héed in any caſe leaſt <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> of the George ſpie you, and ſo follow to the place where my Maſter attends your comming, who I dare ſweare would not for all the Shooes in his ſhop it ſhould be ſo: and therefore good <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> if you chance to ſée her, goe not forward in any caſe, but rather lead her a contrary way, or make ſome queint excuſe, that ſhe may leave your company, and not ſuſpect your pretence. Tuſh quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> let me alone for that, if ſhe follow me ſhe were better no, for I faith I will lead her a dance ſhall make her weary before ſhe have done, and yet ſhall ſhe goe home as very a foole as ſhe came forth, for any goodneſſe ſhe gets at my hand: and therefore farewell <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> quoth ſhe, for I will trudge into Tuttle fields as faſt as I may.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">But looke quoth Robin, you looſe not your Maiden-head by the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> preſently thereupon runnes unto <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> ſaying what chéere <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> how goes the world with all the pretty wenches
<pb facs="tcp:177918:15"/> here? it is a long while ſince I have ſéene you.</p>
            <p>I faith <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> quoth they, we rub out with the reſt, but what is the news with thée?</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Small news quoth Robin yet ſomewhat I have to ſay,</l>
               <l>All Maides that cannot get huſbands muſt preſently marry,</l>
               <l>They that cannot ſtay,</l>
               <l>But heare you Gillian a word by the way.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And with that (rounding her in the eare) he told her that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent it was his Maſters mind that ſhe ſhould méet him in Tuttle fields, charging her if ſhe met <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> of the Crane, that ſhe ſhould in no caſe goe forward, but turne her ſteps ſome other way, for quoth he, my Maſter cannot abide that great rounſefull ſhould come in his company.</p>
            <p>For that let me alone quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> but truſt me <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> it could not have come in a worſe time this twelve moneth, for this day have we a mighty deale of worke to doe, beſide a great bucke that is to be waſht: why then let it reſt till another time quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin:</hi> nay quoth ſhe, hap what hap will, I will goe to him, ſith ſo kindly he ſent for me; and thereupon making her ſelfe quickly ready, into Tuttle fields ſhe got, where at laſt ſhe eſpied <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> with a hand-basket in her hand, who as ſodainly had got a ſight of her, and therefore made a ſhew as if ſhe gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hearbs in the field. I wis that craft ſhall not ſerue your turne quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> I will gather hearbs as faſt as you, though I have as little néed of them as your ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> got him home, and hartily laught to ſée what paines theſe wenches tooke for a husband. O quoth he, what a merry world is this, when Maids runnes a madding for hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bands, with hand-baſkets in their hands? now may I well ſweare what I have ſéene.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Two Maides runne as faſt as they can,</l>
               <l>A mile in the fields to meet with a man.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Then how can men for ſhame ſay that Maidens are proud, diſdainfull or coy, when we find them ſo gentle, that they will run to a man like a Falcon to the Lure, but alas poore ſoules, as good were they to ſéek for a néedle in a bottle of hay, as to ſearch for <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> of the Roſe in Tuttle fields: but hereby doe I know
<pb facs="tcp:177918:16"/> their minds againſt another time, if my Maſter ſhould chance to requeſt their company.</p>
            <p>Thus did round <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> deride them when he found their fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be ſuch: but to leave him to his humor, we will returne to the Maids that were ſo buſie in picking up hearbs in the fields: wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> ſaw that <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> would not away at laſt ſhe came unto her, asking what ſhe made there? Nay what doe you here quoth ſhe? for my owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>art I was ſent for to ſéeke Harts-eaſe, but I can find nothing bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſorrel: Alack good ſoule quoth <hi rend="roman">M g,</hi> and I come to gather thrift but can light on nothing but thiſtles, and therefore I will get m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> waies home as faſt as I can: In doing ſo you ſhall doe well quoth <hi rend="roman">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llian,</hi> but I mean to get ſome Harts eaſe ere I goe away: Nay <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> quoth ſhe, I am ſure I ſhall find thrift as ſoone as you ſhall find Harts-eaſe, but I promiſe you I am out of hope to find any to day, I pray you get you gone then quoth ſhe, what would you ſo faine be rid of my company quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg?</hi> for that word I meane not to be gone yet: I faith <hi rend="roman">Gill I</hi> ſmell a rat.</p>
            <p>Then quoth ſhe you have as good a noſe as our gray Cat: but what rat do you ſmell tell me? <hi rend="roman">I</hi> doubt <hi rend="roman">I</hi> doubt if there be any rat in the field, you would faine catch him in your trap if you knew how; but <hi rend="roman">I</hi> faith <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> you ſhall be deceived as cunning as you are. Then belike qd. <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> you would not have the rat taſte no chéeſe but your owne: all is one for that ſaid <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> but whereſoever he run <hi rend="roman">I</hi> would have him créep into no corner of yours: Your wordes are myſticall quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg.</hi> but if thou art a good wench, let us goe home together: not ſo ſaid <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> as <hi rend="roman">I</hi> came not with you, ſo <hi rend="roman">I</hi> meane not to goe with you.</p>
            <p>No quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg?</hi> before God <hi rend="roman">I</hi> ſweare <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will ſtay as long as thou for thy life. In troth quoth ſhe, <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will make you ſtay till midnight then. Yea quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg?</hi> now as ſure as <hi rend="roman">I</hi> live <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will try that. And in this humor ſometimes they ſat them downe, and ſometimes they ſtalkt round about the field, till it was darke night, and ſo late, that at laſt the watch met with them, who contrary to <hi rend="roman">Gillians</hi> mind, tooke paines to bring them home both together: at what time they gave one another ſuch privie flouts, that the watchmen tooke no little delight to heare
<pb facs="tcp:177918:16"/> it: But their Miſtreſſes that had ſo long miſt them from home though they were very angry with their long abſence. yet were glad they were come againe. And asking where they had been ſo long, the watch-men anſwered, that the one had béene to ſeeke Harts-eaſe, and the other to gather thrift and therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that they ſhould not blame them for ſtaying ſo long to get ſuch good commodities: Verily quoth their Miſtreſſes we will not, for no maruell if they ſtayed out till midnight about ſuch matters, ſéeing we have ſought it this ſeven yeares and could never find it: and in this ſort this jeſt ended.</p>
            <p>Within a while after this, <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> through his long woing, had gotten the good will of his ſwéet-heart, and therefore ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all things ready for his marriage, the mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er being known through <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter, Margaret</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> had tydings there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with the ſooneſt, who comming unto <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> ſaid he was the moſt falſe and unconſtant man in the world. Have I quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> ſet my whole mind upon thée to bée thus ſerved? Nay quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> have I loved thée ſo déerly, and indured ſuch ſorrow for thy ſake, to be thus unkindly caſt off? And I q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth <hi rend="roman">Meg.</hi> that never thought any thing too much for thee, that loved thée bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er then my life, that was at all times ready at thy call, and ready to run or goe at thy commandement to be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeſervedly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, grieves not my heart a little: Nay quoth <hi rend="roman">Gil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ian</hi> could you make me leave my worke to waite upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in Tut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le-fields? Nay did I waite there halfe a day together quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> at thy requeſt to be thus mockt at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hand? Now I wiſh it from my heart, if thou marrieſt any but me, that thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ife may make thée as errant a Cuckold as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ack Coomes. So you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re very charitable quoth <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> to wiſh me no worſe then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou meane to make your husband: but when did I req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to come into Tuttle-fields? What have you ſo weake a memo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y quoth ſhe? I pray you aske your m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n round <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> wrether it were ſo or no: Well quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> how then? wherefore did you no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeake with him at that preſent?</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>You know it comes in an houre, comes not in ſeven yeare,</l>
               <l>Had you met him at that inſtant you had married him cleare.</l>
            </q>
            <p>A vengeance take her quoth <hi>Meg</hi> I could not mée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him for
<pb facs="tcp:177918:17"/> 
               <hi rend="roman">Gillian.</hi> And I could not méet him for <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> a mor in take her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi rend="roman">Gillian. Richard</hi> perceiving by their ſpéech there was a pad lying in the ſtraw, made this reply. It is a ſtrange thing to ſee how you will blame me of diſcourteſie, when the whole fault lyes in your ſelves: had you come at the appointed time, it is likely I had marryed one of you, ſéeing my minde was as well addicted to the one as to the other: Why may it not be yet quoth they, if it pleaſe you? not ſo ſaid <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> you ſpeake too late, men gather no grapes in Ianuary, my wine is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy provided, and my wife prepared: therefore I thanke you both of your good wills, though I be conſtrained of force to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake you the maidens being herewith ſtruck into their dumps, with water in their eyes, and griefe in their hearts went home, to whom <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> carryed two Willow garlands, ſaying.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>You pretty ſoules that forſaken be,</l>
               <l>Take here the branches of the Willow tree,</l>
               <l>And ſing loves farewell joyntly with me.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> being merily inclined, ſhooke off ſorrow in this ſort, and gently taking the willow Garland, ſaid: wherefore is griefe good? can it recall folly paſt? no: can it helpe a matter reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſſe? no: can it reſtore loſſes, or draw us out of danger? no: what then? can griefe make unkind men curteous? no: can it bring long life? no: for it doth rather haſten our death, what then can it do: can it call our friends out of their graves? no: can it reſtore virginity if we chance to loſe our maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head? no: Then wherefore ſhould I grieve? except I went to kill my ſelfe: Nay ſéeing it is ſo, hang ſorrow, I will never care for them that care not for me, and therefore a Figge for the Cocke of <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter:</hi> by this good day I am glad I have ſcapt him, for I doe now conſider I ſhould have never tooke reſt after foure a clocke in the morning, and alas a young married wife would be loath to riſe before eight or nine: beſide that I ſhould never have gone to bed before ten or eleven, or twelve a clocke at night by that meanes, what a deale of time ſhould I have loſt about other women: have him quoth you? now God bleſſe me, I ſweare by <hi rend="roman">Venus,</hi> the faire goddeſſe of ſwéet love, in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> minde I am in, I would not have him, if he had ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:177918:17"/> as would lie in <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter</hi> Hall. And therefore <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> this Willow garland is to me right heartily welcome and I will goe with thée to <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> preſently, and thou ſhalt ſée us weare them rather in triu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ph, then in timerous feare. Well ſaid in good ſadnes, quoth <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> thou art the gallanteſt girle that ever I knew. But when ſhe came to <hi rend="roman">Gillian, Robin</hi> ſtaid for her at the ſtaire foot: they found her ſicke in her bed, fetching many ſore ſighes, to whom <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> ſpake in this manner. Why how now <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> what ſicke a bed? now fle for ſhame, plucke up a good heart woman, let no man triumph ſo much over thée, to ſay thou gaveſt the Crow a pudding, becauſe love would let thée live no longer: he content quoth ſhe, and take courage to thée, death is a ſowre crabbed fellow.</p>
            <p>Ah no quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> death is ſwéet to them that live in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and to none ſhould he be better welcome then to me, who deſires nothing more then death to end my miſeries: What now quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> whoſe Mare is dead? art thou a young wenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, faire and comely, and doſt thou deſpaire of life? and all for love, and all for love. O fond foole worthy to weare a coate with foure elbowes, this were enough if there were no more men in the world but one, but if there were two, why ſhouldſt thou languiſh, much leſſe knowing there is ſo many to he had. O quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> what is all the men in the world to me now I have loſt <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> whoſe love was my life. I pray thée riſe quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> and let us go drinke a quart of Sacke to waſh ſorrow from our hearts. O quoth ſhée, I cannot riſe if you would give me a hundred pound, nor will I riſe for any mans pleaſure: what quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> if your father ſent for you, would you not goe to him? No quoth ſhe: would you not goe to your mother? no: but what if your brethren requeſted you to riſe? Y faith I would not quoth ſhe: ſay that ſome of the Kings Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen intreated your company? never prate, I would not goe to the beſt Lord in the Landqd. <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> nor to no man els in the world: No quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> I am ſute you would. Quoth ſhe if I doe, ſay I am an errant queane, and count me the verleit drab that ever trod on two ſhooes. Nay quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> ſéeing you ſay ſo, I have done, I was about to tell you of a matt, but I
<pb facs="tcp:177918:18"/> ſée it is to ſmall purpoſe, and therefore Ile kéep my breath to coole my pottage.</p>
            <p>A matter ſaid <hi rend="roman">Gillian?</hi> what matter is it ſwéet <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> tell me? N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, no quoth ſhe, it is in vaine, I would wiſh you to couer your ſelfe cloſe, and kéepe your ſelfe warme, leaſt you catch an ague, and ſo good night <hi rend="roman">Gillian.</hi> Nay but <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> quoth ſhe, good <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> if ever thou didſt love me, let me know what this matter is that you ſpeake of, for I ſhall not be in quiet till I know it: tuſh tis but a trifle, a trifle quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> not worth the talke: your ſwéet heart <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> hath ſent his man <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> for you, and as he tels me he hath a token to deliuer you. What quoth <hi rend="roman">Gill,</hi> is that true? Where is <hi rend="roman">Robin?</hi> why comes he not up, truly quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> he counts it more then manners to preſſe into a Maides chamber<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beſide he would be loath to give any cauſe of ſuſpition to any of your fellowes, to thinke Ill of him or you, for now a dayes the world is growne to ſuch a paſſe, that if a Maide doe but looke merrily upon a young man, they will ſay ſtraight, that either ſhe ſhall be his wife, or that ſhe is his harlot: but if they ſée a man come into a womans chamber, they will not ſticke to ſweare that they have béen naught together; for which cauſe <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> intreated me to come unto you, and to certifie you that hée ſtayed at the thrée-Tunnes for your comming: but ſéeing you are a bed I am ſorry I have troubled you ſo much, and therefore farewell good <hi rend="roman">Gillian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O ſtay a little good <hi rend="roman">Meg</hi> quoth ſhe, and I will goe along with you and with that on ſhe ſlipt her petticoate, and made ſuch haſt in dreſſing her ſelfe, that ſhe would not ſtay the plucking on of her ſtockings nor the drawing on of her ſhooes: why how now <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> have you forgot your ſelfe? remember you are Ill and ſicke a bed: Tuſh quoth ſhée I am well enough now: but if you goe foorth to night you are an arrant drab, and a very queane quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg:</hi> Tuſh tis no matter for that, ſaid <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> griefe hath two tongues, to ſay, and to unſay, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I reſpect not what you prate, and therewithall ſhée ran downe the ſtayres after <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> who got <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> to goe before to the thrée Tunnes, where when <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> came, ſhe asked him how his Maſter did, and what his errand was to her.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <pb facs="tcp:177918:18"/>
               <l>Soft: Firſt let us drinke quoth Robin, and then let us talke,</l>
               <l>That we cannot pay for, ſhall be ſet up in chalke.</l>
            </q>
            <p>You ſpeak merrily, quoth <hi rend="roman">Margaret,</hi> whatſoever you meane, but I would I could ſée the wine come once, that I may drink a hearty draught; for ſorrow they ſay is dry, &amp; I find it to be true.</p>
            <q rend="roman">Then drinke hard quoth Robin, and bid ſorrow a due.</q>
            <p>Thus when they had whipt off two or thrée quarts of wine, <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> began to grow as pleaſant as the beſt, and would néeds know of <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> what it was he had to ſay to her; nothing quoth he, but to doe my Maſters commendation, and to deliver you his token. This token, quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian?</hi> What, a Willow gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? is the matter ſo plaine? is this the beſt reward hee can give me for all my good will; had he no body to flout but mée? Yes by my faith, quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> it was his minde that I ſhould beare you company, therefore, looke what he ſent to you, he did the like to mée, and that thou maieſt the better believe me, ſée where it is.</p>
            <p>O intollerable iniury, quoth <hi rend="roman">Gillian,</hi> did I take paines to riſe and come out of my warme bed for this? O how unfortunate have I béene above all other in the world? Well, ſéeing I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not recall what is paſt, I will take this as a iuſt penance for my too much folly; and if <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> will agrée, we will weare theſe diſdainfull branches on his marriage day to his great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, though to our continuall ſorrow: content quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> all is one to mée, looke what thou wilt allow, I will not diſlike, and ſo paying the ſhot, away they went.</p>
            <p>At length, when the marriage day was come, and that the Bride; in the middeſt of her friends was ſet downe to dinner, <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> attyred in red Stammell petticoats, with white linnen ſléeves, and fine Holland Aprons, having their Willow garlands on their heads, entred into the Hall ſinging this ſong:
<floatingText xml:lang="eng" rend="roman" type="song">
                  <body>
                     <lg>
                        <l>WHen fancie firſt fram'd our liking<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> in love,</l>
                        <l>ſing all of greene Willow:</l>
                        <l>And faithfull affection ſuch motion did move,</l>
                        <l>for Willow, Willow, Willow.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:177918:19"/>
                        <l>Where pleaſure was plenty we chanced to be,</l>
                        <l>ſing all of greene Willow:</l>
                        <l>There were we enthral'd of our liberty,</l>
                        <l>and forced to carrie the Willow garland.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This young man we liked and loved full deere,</l>
                        <l>ſing all of greene Willow:</l>
                        <l>And in our hearts-cloſſet we kept him full neere,</l>
                        <l>ſing Willow, Willow, Willow.</l>
                        <l>He was our hearts-pleaſure and all our delight,</l>
                        <l>ſing all of greene Willow:</l>
                        <l>We judg'd him the ſweeteſt of all men in ſight,</l>
                        <l>Who gives us unkindly the Willow garland.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No coſt we accounted too much for his ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ke,</l>
                        <l>ſing all of greene Willow:</l>
                        <l>Fine bands and handkerchers for him we did make,</l>
                        <l>ſing Willow, Willow, Willow.</l>
                        <l>And yet for our good will, our travell and paine,</l>
                        <l>ſing all of greene Willow:</l>
                        <l>We have gotten nothing but ſcorne and diſdaine;</l>
                        <l>as plainly is prov'd by this Willow garland.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then pardon our boldneſſe, thou gentle faire Bride,</l>
                        <l>ſing all of greene Willow:</l>
                        <l>VVe ſpeake by experience of that we have tride,</l>
                        <l>ſing willow, willow, willow.</l>
                        <l>Our over much courteſie bred all our woe,</l>
                        <l>ſing all of greene willow:</l>
                        <l>But never hereafter we meane ſo to doe,</l>
                        <l>For this onely brought us the Willow garland.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Their ſong being thus ended, the Bride ſaid ſhe was heartily ſorry for their hard fortune in love, greatly blaming the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom for his unkindnes; Nay, do not ſo, quoth <hi rend="roman">Meg,</hi> for you ſhal find him kind enough ſoon at night: but ſéeing he hath diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me in this ſort, it ſhall go hard, but I will make ſhift to loſe my maiden-head as ſoone as you ſhall loſe yours, and you ſhall make good haſte, but I wil be before you. O God, quoth ſhe, have
<pb facs="tcp:177918:19"/> I béen ſo chary to kéep my honeſty, and ſo dainty of my maiden-head, that I could ſpare it no man for the love I bore ſo hard-hearted <hi rend="roman">Richard,</hi> &amp; hath he ſerv'd me thus? Well <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> quoth ſhe, let us go, never wil I be ſo tide in affection to one man again while I live; what a deale of time have I loſt and ſpent to no purpoſe ſince I came to <hi rend="roman">London?</hi> and how many kinde offers have I forſaken, &amp; diſdainfully refuſed of many brave Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that would have bin glad of my good will? I thinke I was accurſt to come into his company: Well, I ſay little, but hence forward, hang me if I refuſe reaſon when I am reaſonably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated; truſt me, I would not for a good thing, that my friends in the country ſhould know, that one of my ripe age, bone &amp; big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath all this while liv'd in <hi rend="roman">London</hi> idly, like an unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble member of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth; but if I live, they ſhall heare that I will be better imploy'd, and ſo adue good <hi rend="roman">Gillian.</hi> Thus <hi rend="roman">Margaret</hi> in a melancholy humor went her waies, and in ſhort time after ſhe forſooke <hi rend="roman">Weſtminſter,</hi> &amp; attended on the Kings ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to <hi rend="roman">Bullio,</hi> and while the ſiege laſted, became a landreſſe to the Camp, and never after did ſhe ſet ſtore by her ſelfe, but became common to the call of every man, till ſuch time as all youthfull delights was baniſhed by old age, and in the end ſhe left her life in <hi rend="roman">Iſlington,</hi> being very penitent for all her former offences. <hi rend="roman">Gillian</hi> in the end was well married, and became a very good houſe-kéeper, living in honeſt name and ſame til her dying day.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. How round <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> and his fellowes ſung before the King.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kings Maieſty having royally won the ſtrong town of <hi rend="roman">Bullen,</hi> victoriouſly he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; came into England, and according to his accuſtomed manner, lying at his Palace of Whitehall, divers of the Nobility paſſing up and down Weſtminſter, did many times heare the Shoomakers iournymen ſinging; whoſe ſwéet voyces and pleaſant ſongs was ſo pleaſing in the eares of the hearers, that it cauſed them to ſtay about the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oore to hearken thereunto: <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> above the reſt, declared ſuch cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:177918:20"/> in his ſong, that he ever obtained the chiefeſt praiſe; and no marvell, for his ſkill in prickſong was more then ordinary, for which cauſe the Singing-men of the Abbey did often call him into the Quire. Now you ſhall underſtand, that by their often ſinging in the Shop, the iourneymen of that houſe were noted above all the men in Weſtminſter, and the report of their ſinging went far and néer, in ſo much that at the laſt, the Kings Maieſty had knowledge thereof, who hearing them ſo greatly commended, cauſed them to be ſent for to the Court. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon round <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> and his foure fellows made themſelves rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and their Maſter being of a good mind, againſt the day that they ſhould goe before our King, he ſuted them all at his owne proper coſt, in doublets and hoſe of crimſon Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ety, with black Velvet caps on their heads, and white feathers; on their legs they had fine yellow ſtockings, pumps and pantofles on their féet: by their ſides each of them wore a faire ſword; and in this ſort being brought before his Maieſty, upon their knées they craved pardon for preſuming to come into his royall preſence: The King ſéeing them to be ſuch proper men, &amp; attyred in ſuch Gentleman-like manner, bad them ſtand up: Why my Lords, quoth he, be theſe the merry minded Shoomakers you ſpake of? they are moſt dread Soveraigne, ſaid they; certainly, ſaid our King, you are welcome every one, but who among you is round <hi rend="roman">Robin?</hi>
            </p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>My Liege quoth Robin, that man am I,</l>
               <l>Which in your Graces ſervice will live and die:</l>
               <l>And theſe be my fellowes every one,</l>
               <l>Ready to waite your royall Grace upon.</l>
            </q>
            <p>How now <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> (ſaid our King) What, canſt thou rime?</p>
            <q rend="roman">A little my Liege, <hi rend="blackletterType">quoth he,</hi> as I ſee place and time.</q>
            <p>His Grace laughing heartily at this pleaſant companion, told him that he heard ſay he could ſing well.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Truſt me, quoth Robin, at your Graces requeſt,</l>
               <l>You ſhall well perceive we will doe our beſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Hereupon the King ſate him downe, where many great Lords &amp; Ladies of high eſtate attended on his Highneſſe. And being in the Chriſtmas time, after the maſter of merry diſports
<pb facs="tcp:177918:20"/> had performed all his appointed paſtimes, <hi rend="roman">Robin,</hi> with his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes had liberty to declare their cunning before our King, but the Maieſty of his Princely preſence did ſo amate them, that they were quite daſh'd out of countenance, which his Grace perceiving, gave them many gracious words of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereupon they began in this ſort, ſinging a ſong of the winning of <hi rend="roman">Bullen.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div rend="roman" type="song">
                        <head>The Song of the winning of <hi rend="roman">Bullen</hi> ſung before the King by round Robin and his fellowes.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>IN the moneth of October</l>
                           <l>Our King he would to Dover:</l>
                           <l>By leave of Father and the Sonne:</l>
                           <l>A great armie of men,</l>
                           <l>Well appointed there was then,</l>
                           <l>before our noble King to come;</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>The valiant Lord Admirall,</l>
                           <l>He was captaine Generall,</l>
                           <l>Of all the royall Navie ſent by Sea:</l>
                           <l>The fight was worthie to behold,</l>
                           <l>To ſee the ſhips with ſhining gold,</l>
                           <l>And Flags and Streamers ſailing all the way.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>At Bullen then arriving,</l>
                           <l>With wiſdome well contriving:</l>
                           <l>The armed men were ſet in battle ray;</l>
                           <l>And Bullen was beſieged round,</l>
                           <l>Our men with Drum and Trumpets ſound,</l>
                           <l>Before it march'd couragious that day.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Then marke how all things chanced,</l>
                           <l>Before them was advanced,</l>
                           <l>The royall Standard in the bloodie field;</l>
                           <l>The Frenchmen ſtanding on the walls,</l>
                           <l>To them our Engliſh Heralds calls,</l>
                           <l>Wiſhing in time their Citie for to yeeld.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <pb facs="tcp:177918:21"/>
                           <l>Our King hath ſent to prove you,</l>
                           <l>Becauſe that he doth love you,</l>
                           <l>He profferd mercy if you will imbrace:</l>
                           <l>If you deny his kinde requeſt,</l>
                           <l>And in your obſtinacie reſt,</l>
                           <l>Behold you bring your ſelves in wofull caſe.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Quoth they wee doe deny you,</l>
                           <l>And flatly we defie you,</l>
                           <l>Faire Bullen is a famous Maiden towne;</l>
                           <l>For all the deeds that hath beene done,</l>
                           <l>By conqueſt never was ſhe won,</l>
                           <l>She is a Lady of moſt high renowne.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>VVhen they ſo unadviſed,</l>
                           <l>His proffer had deſpiſed,</l>
                           <l>Our Ordinance began to ſhoote amaine;</l>
                           <l>Continuing eight houres and more,</l>
                           <l>For why our King moſt deeply ſwore,</l>
                           <l>Her Maiden-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d that he would obtaine.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>VVhen thus his Grace had ſpoken,</l>
                           <l>Hee ſent her many a token,</l>
                           <l>Firie balls, and burning brazen rings:</l>
                           <l>Faire broad arrowes ſharpe and ſwift,</l>
                           <l>VVhich came among them with a drift,</l>
                           <l>VVell garniſh'd with the gray gooſe wings.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>This Maiden towne that lately,</l>
                           <l>Did ſhew her ſelfe ſo ſtately,</l>
                           <l>In ſeeking favour, many teares ſhe ſhed:</l>
                           <l>Upon her knees then fell ſhe downe,</l>
                           <l>Saying, O King of high renowne,</l>
                           <l>Save now my life, and take my maidenhead.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Lo, thus her ſelfe ſhe ventred,</l>
                           <l>And ſtreight her ſtreets wee entred,</l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:177918:21"/>
                           <l>And to the market place we marched free:</l>
                           <l>Never a French-man durſt withſtand,</l>
                           <l>To hold a wepon in his hand,</l>
                           <l>For all the gold that ever hee did ſee.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Their ſong being ended, our King eaſt them a purſe with fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty faire angells for a reward, commending both their ſkill and good voyces, and after much pleaſant communication, they had liberty to depart; and when they came home, they told to their Maſter, all their marriment before the King, and what reward his Grace had beſtowed on them; and powring the gold downe upon the Table, the ſame being truly told by their Maſter, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans ſhare came iuſt to five pound a piece. Which, when round <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> ſaw, he ſwore he would beſtow a ſupper upon his Maſter and Miſtreſſe that night, though it coſt him two angels; which his fellowes hearing, and ſéeing <hi rend="roman">Robins</hi> liberall heart to be ſuch, ſaid, they would ioyne with him, and laying their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney together, would have all the Shoomakers in <hi rend="roman">VVeſtminſter</hi> to beare them company.</p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>Content, quoth <hi rend="italic">Robin,</hi> with all my heart;</l>
               <l>And twenty ſhillings I will ſpend for my part:</l>
               <l>And as I am true man, and ſung before our King,</l>
               <l>As much ſhall each of you ſpend before our parting.</l>
               <l>So ſhall we have muſicke and gallant cheere,</l>
               <l>Secke and Sugar, Claret wine, ſtrong Ale and Beare.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This being concluded, they met all together at the ſigne of the Bell, where they were ſo merry as might be, at what time <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> began to blame his Maſter, that had not in thrée yéeres ſpace gotten his Miſtreſſe with childe. Hold thy peace quoth he, all this while I haue but ieſted, but when I fall once in earneſt, thou ſhalt ſée her belly will riſe like a Tun of new Ale: thou know'ſt I am the Cocke of <hi rend="roman">VVeſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q rend="roman">
               <l>I, quoth <hi rend="italic">Robin,</hi> you had that name,</l>
               <l>More for your riſing, than your goodneſſe in <hi rend="italic">Venus</hi> game.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The company at this laugh'd heartily, but ſeven yéeres after this ieſt was remembred; for in all that ſpace had not his wife any child: Wherefore <hi rend="roman">Robin</hi> would often ſay, that either
<pb facs="tcp:177918:22"/> his Maſter was no perfect man, or elſe his Miſtreſſe was in her infancy nouriſhed with the milk of a Mule, which bred ſuch bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe in her; for till her dying day ſhe never had child. And after they had lived together, many yéeres, at laſt, <hi rend="roman">Richard Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteler</hi> dyed, and at his death he did divers good and godly déeds: among many other things he gave to the City of Weſtminſter, a worthy gift to the cheriſhing of the poore inhabitants for ever. He alſo gave toward the reliefe of the poore fatherleſſe children of Chriſts Hoſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tall in London, to the value of forty pound land by the yéere; and in the whole courſe of his life he was a very bountifull man to all the decayed houſekéepers of that place, leaving behind him a worthy example for other men to follow.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V. The pleaſant Story of <hi rend="italic">Peachey</hi> the famous Shoomaker of Fleet-ſtreet in London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Vch about this time, there lived in London a rich Shoomaker, and a gallant houſekéeper; who being a brave man of perſon, bore a mind agréeable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and was therefore of moſt men called luſty <hi rend="roman">Peachey:</hi> hee kept all the yéere forty tall men on worke beſide Prentiſes, and every one hee clothed in tawny coats, which he gave as his livery to them, all with black caps and yellow feathers; and every Sunday and holiday, when this gentleman-like Citizen went to Church in his black gown garded with Velvet, it was his order to have all his men in their liveries to wait upon him, with every man his ſword and buckler, ready at any time, if néed required.</p>
            <p>It came to paſſe upon <hi rend="roman">S. Georges</hi> day, that this iolly Shooma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker (being ſervant to the Duke of Suffolk) went to the Court with all his men after him, to give attendance upon his noble Maſter, which ſome yong Gentlemen more wanton than wiſe, beholding &amp; envying his gallant mind, deviſed how they might picke ſome quarrell, thereby to have occaſion to try his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: quoth they, did you ever know a ſhoomaker, a ſowter, a cobling companion, brave it ſo with the beſt, as this fellow
<pb facs="tcp:177918:22"/> doth? ſée with what a train of hardie ſquires he goes, what ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring lads they be they look as if they would fight with Gargan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua, and make a fray with the great Turk, and yet I durſt lay my life they dare ſcantly kill a Hedgehog: mark him I pray, I warrant you there is never a Knight in this countrey that goes with ſo great a train. Swounes, quoth one, it were a good ſport to draw, &amp; try what they can do. My Maſters be adviſed quoth another, and attempt nothing raſhly: I tell you this fellow is a hardy Coine, he is currant mettley-faith, and whenſoever you try him, ile warrant you ſhall finde he will not flie a foot. With that comes by luſty <hi rend="roman">Tom Stuteley,</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge,</hi> two gallant Sea Captaines, who were attired all in Crimſon Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, in Marriners wide ſtops that reacht to the foot, in watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſilk thrumb hats and white feathers, having Pages attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their weapons, who ſéeing a cluſter of Gentlemen in hard communication at the Court gate, askt what was the matter? Marry Captaine quoth they, we are all beholding to yonder luſty Gallant, that hath ſo many waiting on him with Tawny Coats: Sblood, what is he, quoth <hi rend="roman">Stu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eley?</hi> he ſéemes to be a gallant man ſaid <hi rend="roman">Stra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gwidge,</hi> whatſoever he be: and were it not I ſee him in the Duke of Suffolks liverie, I ſhould have taken him by his train to be ſome Lord at the leaſt: Nay quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley,</hi> he is ſome Knight of good living. Gentlemen quoth they, how your iudgements deceive you: it is certaine he is as good a Shooemaker as any is in Fléetſtreet. What? is he but a Shooemaker quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley?</hi> O how that word makes me ſcratch my elbo: Can a Shooemaker come to the Court with more Servingmen at his héeles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen Captaine <hi rend="roman">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uteley?</hi> ſee how it makes my blood riſe: O the paſſion of my heart, how the villaine ſquares it out? ſée, ſée, what a company of hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome fellowes follow him, it is twenty pound to a penny but they were better borne then their Maſter: not ſo quoth the Gentlem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, but I think their birth and bringing up was much alike, for they be all Shooemakers &amp; his ſtoole companions: now by this iron and ſteell quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley,</hi> were it not that he is attendant on the good Duke, I would have him by the eares preſently. I will lay an hundred pound, and ſtake it dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:177918:23"/> ſtraight, that Captaine <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge</hi> and I will beat him and all his forty men. The Gentlemen being ready to ſet this match forward, greatly commended the Captaines high cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: notwithſtanding they would not hazard their money on ſuch a deſperate match. Well Gentlemen quoth they, you ſay he dwels in Fléet ſtreet, and that he is a Shoomaker, never truſt us more if we become not his cuſtomers, but the croſſeſt cuſtomers ſhall he finde us that ever came to his ſhop for ſhoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. Nay quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley,</hi> we will beſpeak Boots of him, &amp; thus we will raiſe our quarrell: when they are made, if they come not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n eaſie, and ſit on our legs neatly, we will make them pluck them off againe, &amp; preſently we will beat them in péeces about his pate, which if he ſéeme to take in dudgin, and with his men follow us into the ſtreet for revenge, if we make them not leap before us like Monkies, and force them run away like ſhéep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters, let us loſe our credits and Captainſhips for ever.</p>
            <p>But what if you ſhould chance to kill any of them ſaid the Gentlemen: ſwounes quoth they what care we, we are bound to ſea on a gallant voyage, wherein the King hath no ſmall venture, and without us it cannot go forward, ſo that it is not the death of twenty men can ſtay us at home, and therefore when they ſhould be ſéeking of us in Fléetſtréet, we would be ſéeking out the Coaſt of <hi rend="roman">Florida.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay well Captaines quoth they, and no doubt if you do any ſuch thing we ſhall heare of it: for the report thereof will be famous through London. Within a while after <hi rend="roman">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uteley</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge,</hi> having thus determined, came into Fleetſtréet, and making inquiry for <hi rend="roman">Peachies</hi> ſhop, they were by every man directed to the houſe: where, when they were come, they called for the good man of the houſe: the foreman of the ſhop demanded what their will was? why knave quoth they, what careſt thou, let us ſpeak with thy Maſter. Gentlemen quoth he, if you lack any ſuch commodity as we make, you ſhall finde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſufficient to ſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you, for to that end hath my Maſter ſet me in the ſhop. Why Iack-ſauce quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley,</hi> you whorſon peaſant, know you to whom you ſpeak?</p>
            <p>The fellow being very chfleeick, and ſomewhat diſpleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:177918:23"/> at theſe disdainfull ſpeeches, made him this round anſwer: ask you to whom I ſpeak quoth he? I goodman flat cap ſaid <hi rend="roman">Strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge,</hi> we ask to whom you ſpeak? ſir quoth he, I ſpeak to a Velvet ſoole, a ſilken ſlave that knowes not how to governe his tongue: with that <hi rend="roman">Stuteley</hi> ſwore like a mad man and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drew out a dudgin haft dagger that he had by his ſide, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to lay at the fellow, which one of his fellowes ſéeing, flung a Laſt at his head and feld him to the ground: <hi rend="roman">S rangwidge</hi> thereupon drew his ſword, but by that time the fellow had took downe his ſword and buckler, which hung in the ſhop hard at hand, and therewith ſo well defended himſelfe, that <hi rend="roman">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>widge</hi> could do him no hurt: and by that time <hi rend="roman">Stuteley</hi> recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring crald up againe.</p>
            <p>But <hi rend="roman">Peachie</hi> hearing a great hurly burly in the ſhop, came forth and demanded the cauſe of the quarrell? his ſervants told him that thoſe Gentlemen had given the Iourneymen very ill words: How can they chuſe but ſpeak ill quoth <hi rend="roman">Peachie,</hi> for it may be they never learn'd to ſpeak well: whereupon he went unto them ſaying; how now Captaines, how grew this quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell twixt you and my men?</p>
            <p>Thy men quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley?</hi> thy Roags, and thy ſelfe is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that brings them up: ſir quoth <hi rend="roman">Peachie,</hi> your wong me too much, and get you quickly from my doore, or by this ſunne that ſhines, ile ſet you packing, &amp; therefore never think to outface me with great looks, for I tell thée <hi rend="roman">Stu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ley</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge</hi> both, did you look as big as the Devill I feare you not. And you forgot your maners too much to give me ſuch baſe tearms, for I would you well knew I kéepe forty good fellowes in my houſe, that in reſpect of their manhood may ſéeme to be your equals. O intollerable Compariſon quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley,</hi> fleſh and blood cannot beare ſuch abuſe. Ile tell thee what (quoth he) if we two beat not thée and thy forty men, I durſt be hangd up at thy doore. Fie, fie, tis too much oddes quoth <hi rend="roman">Peachy,</hi> dare you two take ten? nay dare you fight with five? Take that and try quoth <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge,</hi> and therewithall gave him a ſound blow on the eare: nay this is too much quoth <hi rend="roman">Peachy,</hi> put up this and put up all: <hi rend="roman">Stuteley</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge</hi> (quoth he) if you be men,
<pb facs="tcp:177918:24"/> meet me in Lincolnes-Inne-fields preſently: Content quoth they, &amp; thereupon went their wayes. <hi rend="roman">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>achie</hi> fetching ſtraight his ſword and buckler, call'd his man <hi rend="roman">Iohn Abridges</hi> to go with him, charging all the reſt not to ſtir out of doores, and ſo into the fields they went, where immediately they met with theſe luſty Caveliers. The Captaines ſéeing him come only with one man, askt if there well all the helpe he had? I will requeſt no more quoth <hi rend="roman">Peachie,</hi> to ſwinge you both out of the fields.</p>
            <p>Brag is a good Dog quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley,</hi> but tell us, haſt thou made thy Will, and ſet thy houſe in order? What if I have not quoth <hi rend="roman">Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chie?</hi> Why then quoth <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge,</hi> for thy wife and childrens ſake go home againe and do it, or elſe get more aide about thée to preſerve thy life.</p>
            <p>Why how now Maſter quoth <hi rend="roman">Iohn Abridges,</hi> come you into the field to fight with women? why theſe be two diſguiſed but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whores ile lay my life, that have more skill in ſcoulding then in fighting: but heare you quoth he, if you be men, leave your foule words, and draw your faire weapons, and becauſe I will ſpare your middle péece, if I ſtrike a ſtroke below the girdle, call me Cut: ſblood ſhall we be thus out-braved quoth <hi rend="roman">Stuteley?</hi> and therewith drawing their weapons, they fell to it luſtily, where <hi rend="roman">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>achie</hi> and his man laid ſo bravely about them, that they beat both the Captaines out of breath, in which fray, <hi rend="roman">Stuteley</hi> was wounded in the head, and <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge</hi> in the ſword arme, but at laſt they were parted by many Gentlemen that came in good time to prevent further miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>The Captaines got them ſtraight to the Surgion, &amp; <hi rend="roman">Peachie</hi> with his man went directly home: and while they were a dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi rend="roman">Peachie</hi> hearing how they were hurt, ſent to <hi rend="roman">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uteley</hi> a kerchiefe by one of his men, and by another a ſcarffe to <hi rend="roman">St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gwidge,</hi> by the third he ſent a bottle of <hi rend="roman">Aqua vitae,</hi> wiſhing them to be of good cheare, for hee intended to be better acquainted with them ere long. The Captaines finding theſe favours to be but flouts, were more grieved thereat, then at their hurt, and therefore with many diſdainfull ſpéeches, they refuſed his proffer'd curteſie.</p>
            <p>And you ſhall underſtand that afterward <hi rend="roman">Peachies</hi> men by
<pb facs="tcp:177918:24"/> two and two at a time, did often méet and fight with them, and ſo narrowly would they watch for them, that they could be in no place in peace, inſomuch that the Captaines found f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghting work enough, &amp; a great deale more then willingly they would, whereby they received many ſcarres and wounds in the body, ſo that lightly they were never out of Surgions hands. Vpon a time it chanced that being upon the point of their voyage, and ſhortly to go to ſea: <hi rend="roman">Stuteley</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge</hi> having béene at the Court, and newly come from my Lord-Admirals ledging, before they came to Charing-croſſe, they were encountred by a couple of <hi rend="roman">Peachies</hi> men, who preſently drew upon them, and laid ſo fréely about, that the two Captaines were glad at length to houſe themſelves for their refuge: Now a plague on them quoth <hi rend="roman">Stu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eley,</hi> ſhall we never be in quiet for theſe quoyſtrels? never were we ſo ferrited before, ſwownes we can no ſooner look into the ſtréets, but theſe ſhoomakers have vs by the eares: a pox on it that ever we medled with the raſcals: ſblood they be as unluckie to be met, as a Hare on a iorney, or a ſergeant on a Sunday morning, for ever one miſchiefe or other followes it, Captaine <hi rend="roman">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rangwidge</hi> (quoth he) there is no other ſhift but to ſéek their friendſhip, otherwiſe we are in danger every houre to be maimed, therefore to kéep our lims ſound aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt we go to Sea, tis beſt to finde meanes to quiet this grudge.</p>
            <p>Then ſaid <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge,</hi> it were good to do ſo, if a man knew how: but you may be ſure they will not eaſily be intreated, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we have ſo mightily abuſed them in ſpéech. Thus they caſt in their mindes divers times by what meanes they might he reconciled: and albeit they ſent divers their friends unto Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi rend="roman">Peachie,</hi> and by his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, yet they would not yéeld, nor give conſent to be appeaſed, nor to put up ſuch wrong as they had received without further revenge: ſo that the Captaines were at length conſtrained to make ſute to the Duke of Suffolk to take up the matter: who moſt honorably performed their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt: and ſo the grudge ended betwixt them, to the great cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of Maſter <hi rend="roman">Peachie,</hi> and all his men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:25"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. How Harrie Nevell, and Tom Drum came to ſerve <hi rend="italic">Peachey</hi> of Fleet-ſtreet.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fame of <hi rend="roman">Peachey,</hi> running through England by meanes of the frayes which he and his men had with <hi rend="roman">Stuteley</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Strangwidge,</hi> it made many of that occupation deſirous to come and dwell with him, for beſide that he was a tall man of his hands, he was alſo an excellent good workman, &amp; therewithall a boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull houſe-kéeper. Among many other that was deſirous of his ſervice, there was one called <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum,</hi> that had a great minde to be his man, a very odde fellow and one that was ſore infected with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin of cogging: this boaſting companion ſitting on a time ſadly at work in his Maſters ſhop at Petworth, and ſéeing the Sun ſhine very faire, made no more to doe but ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſhrowded up S. <hi rend="roman">Hughes</hi> bones, &amp; taking downe his pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe, clapt his pack at his back, and called for his Maſter, who comming into the ſhop, and ſéeing his man prepared to be prauncing abroad, demanded what the matter was that he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed not his buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>O Maſter, qd. he, ſée you not how ſwéetly the Sun ſhines, &amp; how trimly the trées are deckt with green leaves? Well &amp; how then quoth his Maſter? Marry ſir quoth he, having a great mind to heare the ſmall birds ſing, and ſéeing the weather fitter to walk then to work, I called you forth to take my leave and to bid you farewell, I hope ſir I have no wager in your hand.</p>
            <p>Why no quoth his Maſter, thou wilt be ſure to take an order for that, and therefore ſéeing thou wilt be gone, adue. God be with you good maſter quoth he, and farewell all good fellowes of the gentle craft, and therewith he departed.</p>
            <p>The iourneymen of the Towne hearing that <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> went away, according to their ancient cuſtome they gathered themſelves together to drink with him, and to bring him out of town: and to this intent, up they go with him to the ſigne of the Crowne, where they parted not till they had drunk a Stand of Ale drie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:25"/>
            <p>Which being done, they bring him a mile on his way, carry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing a gallon of béere with them: &amp; laſtly there once againe they drink to his good health, and to <hi rend="roman">Chriſpianus</hi> ſoule: and to all the good fellowes of Kerbfoord: which being done, they all ſhook him by the hand, and with hallowing and whooping, ſo long as they can ſée him, they bid him a hundred times farewell. So ſoone as he was gone out of their whooping, the ſweat réeking in his hand, and the Ale in his head, he trips ſo light in the highway, that he féeles not the ground he goes on: and therefore being in a merry vaine, and deſirous to drive out the weary way, as he walks he begins thus pleaſantly to ſing.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" rend="roman" type="song">
               <body>
                  <l>The Primroſe in the greene Forreſt,</l>
                  <l>the Violets they be gay:</l>
                  <l>The double Dazies and the reſt,</l>
                  <l>that trimly decks the way,</l>
                  <l>Doth move the ſpirits with brave delights,</l>
                  <l>whoſe beauties Darlings be:</l>
                  <l>With hey trickfie, trim goe trickfie,</l>
                  <l>under the greene wood tree.</l>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The ſinging of this ſong awaked a young Gentleman whom ſorrow had laid aſleepe on a greene bank by the high wayes ſide. Who having unadviſedly diſpleaſed his Parents, in a cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick humour departed from them, betaking himſelfe to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, thereby to try how fortune would favour him abroad: but having now ſpent all his money, he was in a wofull taking, not knowing what to do, for never had he béene brought up to any trade, whereby he might be able to get a penny at his néed. Wherefore being in this diſtreſſe, he was fully purpoſed to go to London, and there to learne ſome occupation, whereby he might keep himſelf a true man, and not to be driven to ſéek ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour of his friends.</p>
            <p>Now therefore when he heard <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> ſo trimly tune it on the way, raiſing himſelfe from the ſad ground, he awaited his comming, at whoſe ſudden ſight <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> ſtarted like one that had ſpied an Adder: &amp; ſeeing him provided with a good ſword and buckler, ſuppoſed he had béene one that waited for a fat purſe: for which cauſe he began thus to enter parly with
<pb facs="tcp:177918:26"/> him. Good fellow quoth he,, God give you good morrow, but ill ſpéed. Why ſaiſt thou ſo quoth <hi rend="roman">Harrie?</hi> becauſe ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> by the good light of the day thou maiſt ſée to paſſe beſide me, and that by thy ſpéeding ill, I may ſpeed the better: what haſt thou ſuch ſtore of money (quoth <hi rend="roman">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrie</hi>) that thou art loath to loſe it?</p>
            <p>No by my faith quoth he, I have ſo little that I cannot ſpare it: for I aſſure thee all my ſtore is but one poore pennie, and that thou maiſt ſée under my little finger. Why then quoth <hi rend="roman">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrie</hi> if I were minded to aſſault thée, it ſhould be more to rob thée of thy manhood then thy money: but tell me what pack is that thou beareſt at thy back? Marry they be Saint <hi rend="roman">Hughes</hi> bones: Saint <hi rend="roman">Hughes</hi> bones quoth <hi rend="roman">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrie,</hi> what is that? a kind of commodity ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> which I cannot miſſe, for they be my working tooles.</p>
            <p>I pray thée ſaid <hi rend="roman">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrie</hi> what occupation art thou? ſir quoth he, I am a Goldſmith that makes rings for womens héeles: What meaneſt thou by that ſaid <hi rend="roman">Harrie?</hi> I am quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> of the gentle Craft, vulgarly called a Shoomaker.</p>
            <p>The happier thou art quoth <hi rend="roman">Harrie</hi> that thou haſt a trade to live by, for by that means thou carrieſt credit with thée in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place: but tell me good friend, what is thy name, and how far doſt thou travell this way? ſir quoth he, I travell to the next towne, but my iorney is to <hi rend="roman">London,</hi> &amp; as for my name I am not aſhamed to ſhew it: For my name is a Nowne ſubſtantive that may be felt, heard, or underſtood, &amp; to ſpeak the truth I am cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: whoe there, I truſt ſir you ask for no hurt, you are no Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffe nor Bayliffs man, are ye? no not I ſaid <hi rend="roman">Harrie:</hi> Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on you quoth he, I love you the better: for I was never ſo fraid leſt my Hoſteſſe of the <hi rend="roman">George</hi> in <hi rend="roman">Petworth</hi> had ſent you for to arreſt me, for I think I owe her ſome ten Groats of the ſcore, ſet up in very faire Chalk, as one of the principals of her houſe is able to teſtifie: but I pray God ſend her meat, for I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely think I ſhall never ſend her monie. But yet quoth <hi rend="roman">Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> I know not how to call your name: verily ſaid he, I am cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi rend="roman">Thomas Drum,</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Tom D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um</hi> chuſe you whether: Well <hi rend="roman">Thomas</hi> quoth <hi rend="roman">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrie,</hi> I perceive thou art a man &amp; a good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, therefore I will not be ſtrange to open my néed unto thée.
<pb facs="tcp:177918:26"/> I have béene unto my parents untoward, and more then that not knowing when I was well, wilfully I came from them: and now that I have ſpent all my money and worne my ſelfe out of credit, I have vtterly undone my ſelfe, for I am not worth a groat, nor no man will truſt me for two pence. Why then quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> thou art not worth ſo much as goodman Luters lame nagge, for my Lord of <hi rend="roman">Northumberlands</hi> huntſ-man would have given halfe a Crowne for him to have fedde his dogges: notwithſtanding be of good chéere, if thou wilt goe to <hi rend="roman">London</hi> with me, I will heare thy charges, and I faith at the next towne we will be merry and have go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d chéere.</p>
            <p>Alas quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> how can that be ſeeing you have but one penny? I tell thée what quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> wert thou a Shoomaker as I am, thou mightſt goe with a ſingle penny under thy finger, and trauell all <hi rend="roman">England</hi> over and at every good towne have both meate and drinke and lodging of the beſt, and yet have thy pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in ſtore, as when we come to <hi rend="roman">Gilford</hi> you ſhall ſoone ſée. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeve me quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> that is more then any tradeſmen in <hi rend="roman">Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> els can doe.</p>
            <p>Tuſh quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> ſhoomakers will not ſee one another lacke, for it is our vſe if wee know of a good fellow that comes to towne, wanting either meate or money, and that he make himſelfe knowne, he ſhall neede to take no further care, for he ſhall be ſure that the jornymen of that place will not onely give him kinde welcome, but alſo provide him all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary of free coſt: And if he be diſpoſed to worke among them, he ſhall have a Maſter provided by their meanes, without any ſute made by himſelfe at all. Verily quoth <hi rend="roman">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rry,</hi> thou doſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh me with the good report of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paſſing kind and curteous trade, and I would ſpend part of my gentle bloud, to be of the gentle Craft: and for thy curteſie if thou wouldſt teach it mée, I would annoint thée a gentleman for ever: Wilt thou ſay and hold quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom?</hi> Or els hang me ſaid <hi rend="roman">Harry:</hi> then ſaid he annoint me a Gentlemen, and I will ſhape thée for a Shooma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſtraight. Thereupon <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> tooke his knife, and cutting his finger, all to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>meared <hi rend="roman">Tom-Drums</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with his bloud, that hee made him looke like the Image of Bred-ſtréete cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb facs="tcp:177918:27"/> or rather like the Sarazines-head without New-gate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum,</hi> ſéeing him doe ſo, ſaid he might by that means as well annoint him a Ioyner, as a Gentleman: Nay ſaid <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> I do not deceiue thée I warrant thee, ſéeing this blood did ſpring from a Gentleman, if thou wilt not beléeve me, aske all the men in the towne-<hi rend="roman">Malin,</hi> and they will ſay the like.</p>
            <p>Well Ile take thy word quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom.</hi> And therefore looke that preſently thou ſtrip thy ſelfe, for I will caſt thée in a Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers mould by and by: <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> perceiving his meaning did what he willed, and ſo he was ſuted in <hi rend="roman">Toms</hi> attire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> in his; ſo that <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> bore the pike ſtaffe and Saint <hi rend="roman">Hughes</hi> bones: and <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> ſwaggered with his ſword and buckler; and comming in this ſort to <hi rend="roman">Gilford</hi> they were both taken for ſhoomakers, and very hartely welcomed by the jorneymen of that plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> becauſe they never ſaw him before: And at their méeting they askt him and if he could ſing or ſound the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, or play on the Flute, or reco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up his tooles in rime, or manfully handle his pike ſtaffe, or fight with a ſword and buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler? beléeve me quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> I can neither ſound the Trumpet, nor play on the Flute: and beſhroe his noſe that made me a ſhoomaker, for he never taught me to recon up my tooles in rime nor in proſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> hearing him ſay ſo, told them that he made him of an old ſerving m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a new ſhoomaker: When was that (quoth they) marry ſaith he, when I was annointed a Gentleman, I thinke this face can ſhew, that I have gentle blood about me: Why then quoth they thou art but a painted Gentleman, but we muſt account this young man wiſe, that to auoid miſery betakes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to follow miſtery, for cunning continueth when fortune fléeteth, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t it will be hard for ſuch as never were brought up to the bodily labour to frame their fine fingers to any courſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty.</p>
            <p>Not a whit quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> for labour by cuſtome becommeth eaſie. Thou ſaiſt true ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> I durſt lay a good wager I have made more ſhooes in one day then all the jorney-men here have done in a month: with that one of the jorney-men began to chaſe, ſaying, how many a paire of ſhooes haſt thou made in a
<pb facs="tcp:177918:27"/> day? I made quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> when the daies were at longeſt, eight ſcore paire of ſhoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in one day.</p>
            <p>O monſtrous deteſtable lye, (quoth they) and thereupon one ran into the chimney and cried, come againe Clement, come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Whom calſt thou quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> I call Clement carry lye, that runnes Poſte betwixt the <hi rend="roman">Turke,</hi> and the Devill; that he may take his full loading ere he goe, for the beſt jorneyman that ever I knew, never made aboue ten paire in a day in his life: and I will lay my whole yéeres wages with thée, that thou canſt not make twenty paire in a day, as they ought to be: I ſhould be aſhamed but to doe as much as another, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd I never ſaw him yet that could out worke me, yet dare not I take upon me to make a doozen paire of ſhooes in a day: but it is an old ſaying, they brag moſt that can doe leaſt. Why thou Puppie quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> thou houſe Doue, thou Cricket, that never crept further then the chimney corner, tell me what Countries haſt thou trauelled?</p>
            <p>Far enough quoth he, to prove as good a work-man as thou art: I deny that quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> for I have béen where I have ſéene men headed like Dogs, and women of the ſame ſhape, where if thou hadſt offered them a kiſſe, they would have béene ready to have ſnapt off thy noſe: otherſome I have ſéen, that one of their legs hath béen as good as a penthouſe to couer their whole bodies, and yet I have made them ſhooes to ſerve their féet, which I am ſure thou couldeſt never do: nay if thou wilt go with me, if thou ſéeſt me not make an hundred paire of ſhooes from ſun riſing, to ſun ſetting; count me worſe then a ſtinking Mackrell. Now verily thy talke ſtinkes too much (quoth they) and if thou canſt do ſo, never make further jorney, but try the matter héere.</p>
            <p>I tell you quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> I cannot try it in <hi rend="roman">England,</hi> nor yet in <hi rend="roman">France, Spaine,</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Italy,</hi> nor in any part of the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w countries, nor in high <hi rend="roman">Germany, Swea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hland,</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Polonia.</hi> We think no leſſe (quoth they) nor in any part of the world beſide. Yes quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> I can do it as we trauell to <hi rend="roman">Ruſſia,</hi> for there every day is fiue and fiftie of our dayes in length: nay Ile tell you further quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> in ſome parts of the world where I have béen, it is day for halfe a yeare together, and the other halfe yeare is continually
<pb facs="tcp:177918:28"/> night: and goe no further quoth he but into the further part of <hi rend="roman">Scotland,</hi> and you ſhall find one day there (in the month of <hi rend="roman">Iune</hi>) to be foure and twenty houres long: and therefore my Maſters w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ile you live, take héed how you contrary a traue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ler, for the rein you ſhall but be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oray your owne ignorance, and make your ſelves mocking ſtockes to men of knowledge. And trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers (quoth they) uncontrouled, have liberty to vtter what lies they liſt.</p>
            <p>Maſters tell me quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> were you not borne in <hi rend="roman">Arcadia?</hi> No (quoth they) but why aſke you? becauſe ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey doth more abound in plenty of Aſſes, where they ſwarme as thicke as Bées, in <hi rend="roman">Cicily</hi> we have cauſe to give you thanks (quoth they) for calling us Aſſes ſo kindly: not ſo ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> I did but aſke a queſtion; but ſéeing you are ſo cunning, tell mée what Countrey bréeds the beſt Hides, and Leather, and from whence have we the beſt Corke? our beſt Corke comes from <hi rend="roman">Portugall</hi> qd. they, but the beſt Leather grows in our owne land: I deny it quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> there is I confeſſe good Corke in <hi rend="roman">Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> but the beſt grows in <hi rend="roman">Sparta;</hi> but for Hides and Lether there is none comparable to that in <hi rend="roman">Siciona:</hi> where I have made a man a paire of ſhooes that hath laſted him a twelve month to toyle in every day. O tis a gallant Countrey, for I tell you what, there is never a ſhoomaker in <hi rend="roman">England</hi> that kept ſo many men as I did at that time.</p>
            <p>Then ſaid the reſt, thou ſpeakeſt thou knoweſt not what: Maſter <hi rend="roman">Peachy</hi> of Fléetſtréete kéeps continually forty men a work, and the gréen-King of Saint-Martins hath at this time little leſſe then thréeſcore journey-men.</p>
            <p>Then is pretty well quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> but what ſay you to him that for halfe a yéere together, kept waiting on him above a hundred men that never did him ſtitch of work? this was a ſhoomaker of ſome account: but who was that quoth they? Marry quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> ſimple though I ſtand héere, it was my ſelfe, and yet I never made brags of it. O what a ſhameleſſe lyer art thou quoth they, we never knew thée able to kéep one man. Now by this bread ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> you do me mighty wrong, &amp; were it not that ye be all of this gentle Craft, which ſcience I doe ſo greatly love
<pb facs="tcp:177918:28"/> and reuerence, this Iron and ſtéele ſhould make it good upon your fleſh for I tell you once againe, I have béene Maſter of an hundred men, and put ſixtéene ſcore to the hundred: I pray you tell us (quoth they) what men were they? what men were they quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> they were vermin: in troth quoth they we thought as much, and we commend you for telling truth, and we ſuppoſe if you were well ſearcht we ſhould find twenty vermin waiting on you ſtill. But tell vs <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> art thou min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be Maſter <hi rend="roman">Peachies</hi> man? I am quoth he except he will make me his fellow. By the Maſſe (quoth they) then wert thou beſt to have thy wards ready, and thy hilts ſure, for he receives no ſervant before he tries his man-hood; ſo much the better quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> and for that purpoſe I poſte up to <hi rend="roman">London.</hi> Thus having had at <hi rend="roman">Gilford</hi> very good chéere, the jorney-men of the towne paid for all, and beſide gave them money in their purſes to ſpend by the way, and ſo toward <hi rend="roman">London</hi> they went with all ſpeed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 7. How the wilde Knight Sir Iohn Rainsford for burying a Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Prieſt alive, was faine to leave his Lady, and forſake his houſe, till he had obtained his pardon of the King: who meeting with Henry Nevell, and Tom Drum, went with him to ſerve Peachy of Fleet-ſtreet, where for a while he became a Shoomaker.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall underſtand that at this time there lived a gallant Knight called Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn Ransford,</hi> who was for his courage and valiant heart inferour to few men living he kept a bountifull houſe, and a brave company of tall men to waite upon him. To all the poore round about where he dwelt, he was very cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, releeving them daily both with money, and meate; he was a famous Courtier, and in great favour with the King, and the onely thing that diſgraced his vertues, was this, that he was ſomething wild in behaviour, and wilfull in his attempts, often repenting ſadly what he committed raſhly.</p>
            <p>It came to paſſe upon a time that as this couragious Knight was riding home to his own houſe, there was at a certaine vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage,
<pb facs="tcp:177918:29"/> a corps carried to be buried, the deceaſed father of fiue ſmall children and the late husband of a wofull Widdw, whoſe pouerty was ſuch, that ſhe had no money to pay for his buriall: which thing Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn</hi> the pariſh Prieſt doubting, would not by any meanes doe his duty to the dead man, except he might firſt have his money.</p>
            <p>The Widdow and her children, with many teares intreated him to do his office, but he would not be perſwaded, ſaying?</p>
            <p>What you beggers, would you have me open my ſacred lips to invocate and call upon the King of Heaven, to receiue thy huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ſoule, and to perſwade our great Grandmother the earth to wrap his cold body in her warme boſome, for nothing? I tel thée no: firſt ſhall his ſoule frie in the flames of purgatory, till it be as thin as a pancake, and his body remaine aboue ground till the Crowes have pickt his carrion carkaſſe to the bare bones: and therefore leave your puling, and prate no more, leaſt you make me as chollericke as a quaile; and there withall, as he was going away, the poore Widdow falling on her knées, pluckt him by the gowne, ſaying,: good Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> for ſwéet Saint Charity, ſay one <hi rend="roman">Aue Maria,</hi> or one <hi rend="roman">Pater noſter,</hi> and let my poore huſbands corps be couered, though it be but with one handfull of holy ground.</p>
            <p>Nay Dame quoth he, do you remember at the laſt ſhrift how you ſerved me? you would not, no forſooth you would not: and now good Miſtris I will not: no penny, no <hi rend="roman">Pater noſter,</hi> that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at: I pray you now ſée if your honeſty be ſufficient to kéepe your husband from the Crowes. I thought a time would come at length to cry quittance for your coynes: and with that word away he went.</p>
            <p>The poore Widdow ſéeing his obſtinacy, with a heavy heart turned into the high wayes ſide, which was hard adioyning to the Church-yard, and there ſhe and her children wofully begged of the paſſers by, ſome money to bury their fathers dead body.</p>
            <p>At laſt Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> came riding with all his men, of whom the poor Widdow in this manner began to Aske his almes: good Sir quoth ſhe, if ever womans miſery mooved your heart to pitty, give me one penny for Gods ſake, toward the burying of my
<pb facs="tcp:177918:29"/> poore husband: in like manner the children cried, ſaying, one penny for Chriſt his ſake, good Maſter one penny. Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> hearing their lamentable cry, and ſéeing the dead corps lying there, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t why the Prieſt did not bury it?</p>
            <p>O Sir Knight quoth ſhe, I have no money to pay for the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall: and therefore the Prieſt will not doe it. No quoth Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn?</hi> by Gods bleſſed mother I ſweare, Ile make him bury the dead or Ile bury him alive: whereupon he willed one of his men preſently to goe to the Parſonage for the Prieſt, and to bring him thither immediately, his men did ſo, and foorth came Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> in his gowne and corner cap, roughly demanding who would ſpeake with him?</p>
            <p>That would I, quoth Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn Rainesford:</hi> therefore tell me, how comes it to paſſe, that according to order you put not this dead corps into the pit? Sir, quoth he becauſe according to order they will not pay me for my paines.</p>
            <p>Aboue all men quoth Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> Prieſtes ſhould reſpect the poore, and charitably regard the ſtate of the néedy, becauſe they themſelves doe teach charity to the people, and perſwade men unto works of mercy: and therefore Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> ſéeing good déeds are meritorious, doe you win heaven by this good work let the dead poſſeſſe their one: I ſo they ſhall, ſaid the Prieſt ſo I may not looſe my due: for I tell you further, I count it little better then folly, to fill my ſoule with pleaſure by empt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing my purſe with coine: will thou not bury him ſaid the Knight: No not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money ſaid the Prieſt; I pray thée ſaid the Knight let me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thée for this time to doe it, becauſe the woman is poor. Then let me intreat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou to pay me quoth the Prieſt, becauſe you are rich. Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn Rainsford</hi> ſéeing him ſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo peremptory on his points, ſwore a déep oath, that it were beſt for him to bury him, or quoth he. Ile bury thée; bury me ſaid the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt a fig for you, and bury blind bayard when he is dead, or the dogs that your Hanks will not eate. The Knight at theſe words being marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous angry commanded his men to take him up &amp; caſt him into the grave: his men made no more to do, but preſently upon their Maſters word tooke up the Prieſt, and wrapping him round in his gowne, put him quicke into the grave, and the
<pb facs="tcp:177918:30"/> reſt caſt earth upon him as faſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s they could, at what time the Prieſt cried out, hold, hold, for Gods ſake, let me riſe and I will bury him Nay ſoft quoth the Knight, thou art not like to riſe, no riſing héere before the generall reſurrection, that thou ſhalt riſe to judgement, and therefore quicke as he was they bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him, which being done, he commanded the Sexton to make another grave for the dead man, and ſending for another Prieſt, he; ſat him if he wold bury the dead without money, who make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twenty legs, ſhivering and ſhaking with feare, anſwered I forſooth with all my heart, for they are knaves and no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that will not doe it.</p>
            <p>Now when the dead man was buried, the Knight gave the poore Widdow an angell in gold to comfort her and her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſo rode his way.</p>
            <p>When he came home, he fold his Lady what he had done; who greatly grieving thereat, wiſht he had pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for twenty bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, rather then he had made that one buriall. Tis done now ſaid the Knight, and undone it cannot be againe, though with griefe I ſhould kill my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now you ſhall underſtand, that the Deane of the Dioces, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving word hereof, rode up preſently to <hi rend="roman">London</hi> and made a great complaint thereof unto the King, which when his grace had conſidered he was very wroth thereat and therefore ſent down purſevants to apprehend the Knight, but he before had forſaken his houſe, and wandred in diſguiſe up and downe the Countrey. His Lady in the meane ſpace made great ſuite for his pardon, being therein aſſiſted by divers great Counſellors, and Noble Lords, who much lamented the Knights caſe: notwithſtanding they could hardly forbeare laughing many times when they thought upon this mad pranke.</p>
            <p>But as Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn</hi> diſguiſedly wandred, he chanced twixt <hi rend="roman">Gilford</hi> and <hi rend="roman">London</hi> to light in the company with <hi rend="roman">Harry Nevell</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum:</hi> But <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> vewing him well in the face, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cried by his countenance what he was, and maruelling much to ſée him in ſuch diſtreſſe, made himſelfe not known, but ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him in this ſort.</p>
            <p>Sir quoth he, whither do you wander this way, or to what
<pb facs="tcp:177918:30"/> place trauell you? Gentle youth quoth he, fitly doſt thou aske me whither I wander, ſeeing indéed we doe all but wander in this vale of miſery: doſt thou demand whither I trauell? nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aske wherefore I trauell, or wherewith I trauell? and then could I ſoone anſwer thée: ſbones quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> I durſt lay a haporth of Ale, that the Peaſant is in labour with love.</p>
            <p>Nay quoth Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> hadſt thou ſaid I trauelled with griefe, and that I was in labour with ſorrow, then hadſt thou ſaid right, for I may ſay to thée, I have had a ſore labour continually this month in paine, and yet is not the time of my deliuerance come, wherein I ſhould be fréed from this untoward child of care: thou didſt thinke I was in love, O would to God it were ſo, for while I was in love, my dayes ran foorth in pleſant houres, but I am caſt off like a lumpe of earth from the gardiners ſpade: I love, but I am not beloved, but rather hated and deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>Tuſh quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> bridle theſe fooliſh paſſions, for Ile tell thée what, hunger aſſwageth love, and ſo doth time, but if thou be not able to doe any of theſe, then to take an halter, which if thou doeſt vſe as it ought, if ever thou complaine more, of ſorrow or care, never truſt my word for a cupple of blacke puddings.</p>
            <p>Belike, ſaid Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> thou haſt béen ſome hangman that thou art ſo cunning in the nature of an halter: but howſoever thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteſt it good, yet it is an Ill word foure times a yéer at New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, and as ſmall comfort is it to me to heare it rehearſt at this time.</p>
            <p>Indéed ſaid <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> theſe are unſauory tearmes to be ſpoken to a ſorrowfull man: neither have any of us great cauſe to be merry at this méeting, conſidering the hard caſes wée are in, that are both maſterleſſe, and moneyleſſe, which if God doe not ſoone ſend us, will cauſe our ſodaine miſery.</p>
            <p>With that the Knight turning his head, pluckt his hat to his eyes to hide the teares that trickled down his face, ſaying, O my maſters, want of money cannot make a man miſerable, if he have health and liberty, to worke for his liding, but indéed the frownes of a good Maſter, the diſpleaſure of a good Maſter, the hate of a good maſter, may eaſily make a ſervant miſerable, as by mine own experience <hi rend="roman">I</hi> have ſéen, &amp; to my grief but lately felt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:31"/>
            <p>What man, be blith ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> and never grieve ſo much for the Ill will of a Maſter. God kéepe me from being of thy mind, for if I ſhould have grieved at the Ill will of every Maſter that I have ſerued, I verely thinke I ſhould have kild a proper man long ere this; for I am ſure I have had as many Maſters, as there are Market townes in <hi rend="roman">England,</hi> and yet perhaps quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> none ſo good a Maſter as his was.</p>
            <p>Never did man ſpeake truer word ſaid the Knight for he was to me good kind and liberall, but howſoever he hath baniſht me his houſe, yet ſhall my heart ſerue him while I live: now doth it come in my mind, how happy they are that live in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: how bleſſed they be that enioy his preſence; O were my head once againe ſhadowed under his faire roofe, it would expell all unquiet thoughts, which like milſtones preſſeth downe my hearts comfort.</p>
            <p>What, would you goe dwell with him againe quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom?</hi> fie what a baſe mind doe you beare; were it to me, by this fleſh and bloud, I would rather run as far as <hi rend="roman">Ieruſalem</hi> to ſéeke a Maſter. <hi rend="roman">Tom, Tom</hi> (ſaid the Knight) I know this, wealth makes men lofty, but want makes men lowly, and commonly gentle. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have proud ſervants, but had I béene as wiſe, as I was wilfull, I might have led a happy life, but if teares might ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie for mine offence, I would quickly recouer his favour.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the wofull Knight would have parted their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> ſecretly conferring with him had knowledge how his griefe grew, and making themſelves known the one to the other, agréed to goe to <hi rend="roman">London</hi> together, and there to try what fortune would befall them.</p>
            <p>The Knight tooke great comfort by this conference, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtore of gold about him, made them great chéere at <hi rend="roman">King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> and in the end was content to take their counſaile: and comming into Fléet-ſtréete, <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> brought them to <hi rend="roman">Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi> houſe, where ſuch meanes was made: that at laſt upon the tryall of their manhood, they were all entertained; and ſo well <hi rend="roman">Peachy</hi> liked of Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> that he vowed he ſhould not be his man, but his fellow.</p>
            <p>Within ſhort time after the French-men had landed in the
<pb facs="tcp:177918:31"/> Ile of Wight, about two thouſand men of warre, who burned and ſpoyled the Country very ſore for which cauſe the King had made ready an army of men to goe thither. <hi rend="roman">Peachy</hi> at his owne proper coſt, ſet forth thirty of his owne ſervants, well armed at all eſſayes, and himſelfe as Captaine over them muſtred before the King: who liked ſo well of them, that he choſe out ſeaven of that company for his owne Guard; at what time Sir <hi rend="roman">Iohn,</hi> in diſguiſed manner ſhewed there ſuch good ſervice, that thereby he won his Majeſties high favour, and was by him moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pardoned. <hi rend="roman">Peachy</hi> was hereupon made the Kings Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, who lived long after in great favour and eſtimation, both with his Majeſty, &amp; all the honourable Lords of the Court.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 8. Of Tom Drums vants, and his rare intertainment at Miſtris Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers houſe, the faire Widdow of Fleet-ſtreet.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here lived in Fléet-ſtréete at this time a faire Widdow, who was famous for her beauty, as ſhe was eſtéemed for her wealth, ſhe was beloved of many Gentlemen, and ſued unto by divers Citizens, but ſo déepe was the memory of her late husband ingrauen in her heart, that ſhe vtterly refuſed marriage leading a ſober and ſolemne life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Harry Nevell</hi> having his heart fired with the bright beams of this blazing Comet, ſought all meanes poſſible to quench the heate thereof with the floudes of her favourable curteſie: and lacking meanes to bring himſelfe acquainted with ſo curious a péece, be wrayed by his outward ſighs, his inward ſorrows: which upon a time, <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> perceiving, demanded the cauſe of his late conceiued griefe, ſaying, How now <hi rend="roman">Hall,</hi> what wind blowes ſo bleake on your chéekes now? tell me mad wag, hath <hi rend="roman">Cupid</hi> and you had a combate lately? why lookeſt thou ſo ſad? hath the blind ſlave giuen thée a bloody noſe, or a broken head? Oh, no <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> quoth he, that little tyrant aimes at no other part but the heart, therefore tis my heart, and not my head that bléeds. With whom <hi rend="roman">Hall,</hi> with whom art thou in love, tell me man? it may be I may pleaſure thée more in that matter then my Lord Major: therefore I faith <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> ſay who is it? never be afraid
<pb facs="tcp:177918:32"/> man to unbuckle your Budget of cloſe counſell to me, for if I be wray your ſecrets call me dogs-noſe, and ſpit in my face like a young kitling.</p>
            <p>I tell thée <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> I am holden in greater account among women then you are aware, and they will more willingly ſhew their ſecrets to me then to their ghoſtly father: But art thou ſo in favour with fine wenches quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I faith Sir I, quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> and I fro I have not lived thus long, but I know how to make a woman love me, by a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning tricke that I have: I durſt lay my life, I will make a dozen maids runne after me twenty miles for one nights lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, ſtriving, who ſhould firſt beſtow her maiden-head on me.</p>
            <p>That tricke ſurpaſſes of all that ever I heard quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> Ile tell thée once what a merry pranke I plaid, God forgive me for it: upon a time on a Saterday in the morning, I went into Eaſt cheape of purpoſe to ſpie what pretty wenches came to Market where I ſaw a great many as freſh as flowers in <hi rend="roman">May,</hi> tripping up and down the ſtréets with hand baſkets in their hands, in red ſtammell petticoates, cleane neckerchers and fine holland aprons as white as a Lilly: I did no more but carry the right leg of a Turtle under my left arme, and immediately the wenches were ſo inamoured with my fight that they forſooke the butchers ſhops, and inticed me into a Tauerne, where they ſpent all the money they ſhould have laid out at Market, onely to make me merry: and never had I ſo much to doe, as to be rid of their company where they were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall together by the eares, for the kiſſes they would have beſtowed upon me.</p>
            <p>But it may be quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> your art would faile me now, to help your friend at a dead lift: not ſo ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> and therefore if there be any in this ſtréet that thou haſt a mind unto, thou ſhalt carry but the head of a dead crow about thée, &amp; it ſhall be of force to bring her to thy bed were it fine Miſtres <hi rend="roman">Farmer</hi> her ſelf. But art thou acquainted with her quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> or doſt thou thinke thou couldſt prefer a friend to her ſpéech? I quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> why I tell thée I am more familiar with her then with <hi rend="roman">Doll</hi> our kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hen-drudge: why man ſhe will doe any thing at my requeſt, nay, I can command her in ſome ſort, for I tell thee
<pb facs="tcp:177918:32"/> ſhe will not ſcant be ſéene in the ſtréet, though ſome would give her twenty pound for every ſtep, and I did but ſlightly requeſt her to walke into the fields with me, and ſtraight ſhe went, and I never come into the houſe, but I have ſuch entertainment as no man hath the like: for as ſoone as ever ſhe ſées me ſet footing on her checkquerd pavement, preſently with a ſmiling looke, ſhe méetes me halfe way ſaying, what my friend <hi rend="roman">Tom-Drum?</hi> honeſt <hi rend="roman">Thomas,</hi> by my Chriſtian ſoule, hartily welcome: then ſtraight a chair and a cuſhion is fetcht for me, and the beſt chéere in the houſe is ſet on the table, and then ſitting downe by my ſide in her ſilken gowne, ſhe ſhakes me by the hand and bids me welcome, and ſo laying meate on my trencher with a ſilver forke ſhe wiſhes me frolicke, at what time all the ſecrets of her heart ſhe imparts unto me, craving my opinion in the premiſes. I aſſure thée ſaid <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> thoſe are high favours, well be wray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great friendſhip that ſhe beares thée, and <hi rend="roman">I</hi> much mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that thou being a young man, wilt not ſéeke a wife that is ſo wealthy, and ſo make thy ſelfe famous, by marrying Miſtris Farmer, for it is likely ſhe could well away to make him her husband, to whom ſhe opens her hearts ſecrets.</p>
            <p>Tis true quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> and <hi rend="roman">I</hi> know that if <hi rend="roman">I</hi> ſpoke but halfe a word ſhe would never deny me: nay ſhe would ſpend ten of her twelve ſilver Apoſtles, on condition <hi rend="roman">I</hi> would vouchſafe to be her huſband. But wot you what <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> it is well known though Lillies be faire in ſhew, they be foule in ſmell, and women as they are beautifull ſo are they deceitfull: beſide, Miſtris Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is too old for me.</p>
            <p>Too old quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry?</hi> why man ſhe is not ſo old as charing-Croſſe for her gate is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> crooked nor her face withered: but were ſhe an hundr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d yeare old, having ſo ſtrong a body and ſo fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a face ſhe were not in my opinion much to be miſlikt; yet in my conſcience <hi rend="roman">I</hi> thinke, ſince firſt her faire eyes beheld the bright ſunne, ſhe never taſted the fruites of twenty flouriſhing Somers: nor ſcant felt the nipping froſtes of ninetéene cold winters, and therefore her age néed be no hurt to her marria<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. Ile tell thée my mind quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> after a wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is paſt ſixtéene yéeres old, <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will not give fiftéene blew buttons for her: but tell
<pb facs="tcp:177918:33"/> me <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> doſt thou like her? if thou doſt ſay ſo, and I will war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant her thy owne.</p>
            <p>Gentle <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> the true figure of unfained friendſhip, and the aſſured Map of manhood, doe but prefer me to her acquaintance, and I will requeſt no greater curteſie. Here is my hand quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> it ſhall be done, and on Thurſday at night next we will goe thither, and then thou ſhalt ſée whether <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> can command any thing in Miſtreſſe Farmers houſe or no. The day being thus ſet downe, <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> had prepared himſelfe a faire ſute of apparell againſt the time, and beſide had bought certaine giftes to beſtow on the faire Widdow: <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> in like ſort had dreſt himſelfe in the beſt manner he might, ſtill bearing <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> in hand that none in the world ſhould be better welcome then he to the Widdow: which God wot was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo, for ſhe never reſpected him but onely for the ſhooes he brou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht her: but you ſhall ſée how it fell out. The day being come, <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> taking <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> by the hand, and comming to the Widdows doore, took hold on the Bell and rung thereat ſo luſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if he had béene bound ſeaven yeares Prentiſe to a Sexton: whereupon one of the Prentiſes came ſtraight to the doore, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who is there? Sirra, quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum,</hi> tis I, open the doore; the fellow ſéeing it to be <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum,</hi> with a frown askt him what he would have? who anſwered, be would ſpeake with his Miſtris. My Miſtris is buſie quoth the fellow, cannot I doe your errand? No marry can you not quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> I muſt ſpeak with her my ſelfe: then ſtay a little quoth the boy, and I will tell, and with that in he went, leaving <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> ſtill at the doore, where they ſate till their féet waxt cold before the boy returned. By the Maſſe quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> whatſoever your credit with the Miſtris is I know not, but the curteſie is ſmall that is ſhewen you by her man: Tuſh quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> what will you have of a rude unmannerly boy? if any of the Maids had come to the doore, we had béene long ere this brought to their Miſtris preſence: therefore once againe I will vſe the help of the Bell-rope.</p>
            <p>At his ſecond ringing, out comes one of the Maids, ſaying with a ſhrill voyce: who the Divell is at the doore, that kéepes ſuch a ringing? why you queane quoth he, tis I, what <hi rend="roman">Tom-Drum</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177918:33"/> quoth ſhée, what would you have? I would ſpeak with your miſtreſſe quoth he: truſt me ſaid the maid, you cannot ſpeake with her now, ſhe is at ſupper with two or thrée that are ſutors Maſter Doctor <hi rend="roman">Burket</hi> is one, and Maſter Alderman <hi rend="roman">larvice</hi> the other: tut quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> tell me not of ſutors but tell her that <hi rend="roman">I</hi> am here, then good enough: well <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will quoth ſhée, and with that, claps to the dore againe, and kéepes them ſtill without. This geare workes but ill-favouredly, yet ſaid <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> and you are little beholding either to the men, or to the maids, for ought that <hi rend="roman">I</hi> ſée<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that will not ſhew you ſo much favour to ſtay within dores: 'tis no matter, <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> quoth he, but if their Miſtreſſe ſhould know this ſhe would ſwinge their co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for it: and with that, one of the bayes opening the doore, told <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> that his miſtreſſe wold have him ſend up his errand, ſblood quoth he, is ſhe ſo ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tely that ſhe will not come downe? <hi rend="roman">I</hi> haue ſeene the day when ſhe would have bin glad to have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with me: I quoth the fellow, it may be ſo, when you have brought her a new paire of ſhoes, that hath pincht her at the toes. Come <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> ſaid <hi rend="roman">Tom, I</hi> will take the paines for this once to goe up to her, by my faith but you ſhall not ſaid the fellow, and therefore kéepe you backe for you come not in here: <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> ſéeing himſelfe thus diſgrac'd before his fellow <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> (being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry) askt if this were the beſt entertainment that they could affoord their Miſtreſſes Friends? And therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all began to ſtruggle with them: which their miſtreſſe hearing, ſtarted from the table, and ſuddenly came to ſée what the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was, who being certified of <hi rend="roman">Tom Drums</hi> ſawcineſſe, began thus ſharpely to check him, why fellow quoth ſhe art thou mad, that thus uncivilly thou behaveſt thy ſelf? what haſt thou to ſay to me, that thou art thus importunate? no hurt quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h he, but that this gentleman and I would have beſtowed a galland of wine to have had three or foure houres talke with you.</p>
            <p>I tell thee ſaid ſhe, I am not now at leaſure, and therefore good honeſty trouble me no more: neither is it my wont to be won with wine at any time; gods Lord quoth he are you grown ſo coy? if you and I were alone I know <hi rend="roman">I</hi> ſhould finde you more milde: what muſt no man but Doctor <hi rend="roman">Burket</hi> caſt your
<pb facs="tcp:177918:34"/> water? is his Phiſicke in moſt requeſt? well I meane to be better entertained ere <hi rend="roman">I</hi> goe, for there is never a Felmming of them all ſhall out face me, by the morrow Maſſe <hi rend="roman">I</hi> ſweare. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris <hi rend="roman">Farmar</hi> ſeeing him ſo furious, anſwered he ſhould have preſent entertainment according to his deſert; whereupon ſhe made no more to doe, but quietly went to her ſervants, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to thruſt him out by the head and ſhoulders: which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they performed. But <hi rend="roman">Harry</hi> was by her v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry modeſtly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that if he had occaſion of any ſpéech with her, the next day h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould come and be patiently heard and gently anſwered: with which words after ſhe had drunke to him in a gobblet of Claret wine, he departed, and going home he told <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> he was highly beholding to him for his curteſie in preferring his ſute to Miſtris <hi rend="roman">Farmer:</hi> ſurely quoth hée, you are in very high favour with the faire woman, and ſo it ſéemed by your great entertainment: I pray thée <hi rend="roman">Tom</hi> tell me how taſted the meat which ſhe ſet on thy trencher with her ſilver forke: and what ſecret was that ſhée told in thy eare? truſt me thou art precious in her eies, for ſhe was as glad to ſée thée, as one had given her a ruſh, for when after many hot wordes ſhe heard thée draw thy breath ſo ſhort, ſhe for very pitty tumbled thée out into the ſtréet to take more apre: well quoth <hi rend="roman">Tom,</hi> floute on, but I am well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſerved, Ile lay my life had I not brought thée with me, never a man ſhould have had more welcome then I: and now <hi rend="roman">I</hi> conſider with my ſelfe that it did anger her to the heart when ſhe ſaw I was purpoſed to make another copartner of her preſence: but it ſhall teach me wit while I live, for I remember an old ſaying, love and Lordſhip brookes no fellowſhip; but when this matter was made known to the reſt of the jorneymen, <hi rend="roman">Tom-Drums</hi> entertainment was ſpoke of in every place, inſomuch that it is to this day a proverb amongſt us, that where it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a man ſhall not be welcomed, they will ſay he is like to have <hi rend="roman">Tom Drums</hi> entertainment. And to auoid the flouts that were daily given him, poore <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> forſooke Fléet-ſtréet, and at laſt went into <hi rend="roman">Scotland,</hi> being preſt for a Drummer at <hi rend="roman">Muskelbrough</hi> field, where the noble Duke of <hi rend="roman">Sommerſet</hi> &amp; the Earle of <hi rend="roman">Warwick</hi> were ſent with a noble army where, Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:177918:34"/> and Scots méeting, there was ſought a cruell battle, the victory whereof fell to the Engliſhmen at what time there was ſlaine of the Scots to the number of 14. Thouſand, and fiftéene hundred taken priſoners, where we will leave <hi rend="roman">Tom Drum</hi> till his returne, making mention how <hi rend="roman">Harry Nevell</hi> behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the meane ſpace in <hi rend="roman">London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP 9. How Harry Nevell, wooed Miſtris Farmer and deceived Doctor Burket: and how they were both beguiled by a Prentice that dwelt in the houſe, who in the end married her.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Iſtris <hi rend="roman">Farmer</hi> fiering the hearts of many with her beauty, was wond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſly wooed by Doctor <hi rend="roman">Burket,</hi> who would give unto her divers rich gifts, the which though they were faire and coſtly, yet Miſtris <hi rend="roman">Farmer</hi> would hardly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them, but even what he in a manner by perforce conſtrained her to take, leaſt by his cunning he ſhould inſert therein ſome matter more then ordinary, that might moove any motion of love, contrary to her naturall inclination: upon a time <hi rend="roman">Harry Nevell</hi> comming thether, and finding the Doctor very diligent to bréed the Widdows content, whereby he greatly hindred his procéedings, caſt in his mind how he might diſburden the houſe of the Doctor and get opportunity to prefer his owne ſute. At laſt lighting on a device fit for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, in this ſort he delt with the Doctor; there was an Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an woman that at Black-wall was in trauell with child, and had ſuch hard labour, that ſhe was much lamented among all the wives that dwelt thereabout. <hi rend="roman">Harry Nevell</hi> comming that way, and hearing thereof, thought it a fit matter to imploy Doctor <hi rend="roman">Burket</hi> about, while in the meane ſpace he might the better be, wray his affection to the Widdow.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he ſent one to him attyred like a ſerving man, booted and ſpurd, who comming to the Widdows houſe all in a ſweate; laid load on the doore demanding for Maſter Doctor: what would you with him quoth one of the Maids? marry quoth he, my Lady <hi rend="roman">Sunborne</hi> hath ſent for him in all poſt haſt, and therefore I pray you let me ſpeake with him. I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb facs="tcp:177918:35"/> doe your errand ſaid the maid, whereupon running up ſhe told him that my Lady <hi rend="roman">Sunborne</hi> hath ſent a meſſenger in very great haſt to ſpeake with him. Doctor <hi rend="roman">Burket</hi> hearing that, and being well acquainted with the Lady <hi rend="roman">Swinborne,</hi> took leave of the Widdow &amp; went to the meſſenger, ſaying how now good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, what would my good Lady haue with me? Sir ſaid the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, ſhe would deſire you if ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r you did tender the life of a Lady, to make no delay, but preſently to put your ſelfe a horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, &amp; come to her, for ſhe is wondrous ſick: I am ſory for that ſaid the Doctor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; ſurely I will make all ſpéed poſſible to come to her: whereupon the Doctor tooke horſe and immediatly went with the ſeruingman. <hi rend="roman">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rry</hi> hearing of his departure, came to the Widdow with a ſmiling countenance and thus merily began to wooe her.</p>
            <p>Now Miſtris <hi rend="roman">Farmer,</hi> happy it is that a yongman once in a moneth may find a moment of time to talk with you: truth it is that your good graces haue greatly bound me in affection to you, ſo that onely aboue all the women in the world <hi rend="roman">I</hi> haue ſetled my delight in your love, &amp; if it ſhall pleaſe you to requite my good will with the like kindneſſe, I ſhall account my birth day bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; remaine your faithfull friend for ever. Gentle man quoth ſhe, for your good will, I thank you, but I would haue you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the leſſe you love me, the better I ſhall like you, for your delights &amp; mine are not alike, I haue ſetled my fancy on a ſingle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, being a Widdow unméete to marry, &amp; unapt to loue; once indeed I had learned that leſſon, but my ſchole maſter being untimely dead that taught me, I grew forgetfull of all thoſe principles &amp; then I ſwore neuer to follow that ſtudy more: wherefore if you will become a faithfull friend to me, let me be aſſured thereof by this, that from hencefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h you will not any more trouble me with this matter, &amp; thereby you ſhall bind me to think the better of you while I know you: &amp; doe not think I ſpeak this of any affection procéeding from my ſelf to any other, or for the deſire of any benefit proferred by any other to me.</p>
            <p>Faire Miſtris quoth <hi rend="roman">Harry,</hi> I know it is the cuſtome of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to make their denials unto their louers, &amp; ſtrictly to ſtand on nice points, becauſe they will not be accounted eaſily won,
<pb facs="tcp:177918:35"/> or ſoone entreated: alack déere Dame conſider nature did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne your face with ſuch incomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rable beauty, &amp; framed every other part ſo full of excellency, to wound men with woe, but to worke their content.</p>
            <p>Wherefore now in the <hi rend="roman">Aprill</hi> of your yeares, &amp; the ſwéet ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of your dayes, baniſh not the pleaſures incident to bright beauty, but honour <hi rend="roman">London</hi> ſtréets with the faire fruite of your womb &amp; make me bleſſed by being father to the iſſue of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate body; &amp; though your beauty as the ſpring doth yet yearely grow, yet in the black winter of old age it will not be ſo, &amp; we ſée by daily experience, that flowers not gathered in time rot &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume themſelves: wherfore in my opinion you ſhould doe the world intollerable wrong to live like a fruitleſſe figtrée.</p>
            <p>Nay then Sir quoth ſhe, I perceive you will grow trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ſhew your ſelfe no ſuch man as you profeſſe your ſelfe: and ſéeing among many I requeſt but one thing at your hands, and you refuſe to doe it for my ſake, I may ſay your frind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is more in words then in works: wherefore I perceive I muſt be conſtrained to call my Maid for a cup of voyding béere ere you will depart.</p>
            <p>Nay Miſtris quoth he, I will ſaue you that labour, ſéeing your love commands me, &amp; I pray God grant you a more favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mind at our next m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eting, &amp; with theſe words he departed.</p>
            <p>Now you ſhall underſtand, that this gallant Widdow had in her houſe a very proper youth which was one of her aprentices who had a long time borne his Miſtris great good will: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he became ſo diligent &amp; carefull about all things committed to his charge that thereby he won much commendations among all the neighbors, &amp; was for the ſame highly eſtéemed of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris: who after he had long concealed his grief at laſt unburden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe of ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſorrow, by making a friend privy to his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, who comforted him in this ſort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tuſh m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> quoth he what though ſhe be thy Miſtris, &amp; thou her prentiſe, be not aſhamed to ſhew thy affection to her: ſhe is a woman wiſe &amp; modeſt, and one that however ſhe anſwers thy demand, will not think worſe of thée for thy good will: therefore try her, thou knoweſt not how fortune may favour thy ſute, and the worſt is ſhe can
<pb facs="tcp:177918:36"/> but ſay ſhée nay: O quoth he, if I were out of my years. I could have ſome heart to wooe her, but having yet thrée quarters of a yéere to ſerve, it may be ſome hindrance to my fréedome if ſhe ſhould prove fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ward.</p>
            <p>Tuſh ſtand not on thoſe tearms, ſaid his friend <hi rend="roman">Francis,</hi> ſhe will never requite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>indnes with ſuch diſcurteſſe, and therefore <hi rend="roman">William</hi> prove not a foole by being too fearefull.</p>
            <p>O my deare friend <hi rend="roman">Francis,</hi> quoth he, how can I ſuppoſe I ſhould ſpéed well, ſéeing ſhe diſdains Doctor <hi rend="roman">Burket,</hi> and refuſes Maſter Alderman, &amp; will ſhew no countenance to gallant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi rend="roman">Nevell;</hi> what a bad reaſon is this quoth <hi rend="roman">Francis,</hi> ſome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abide to eate of a Pig: ſome to taſte of an Eele, otherſome are ſicke if they ſée but a Crab, and divers cannot away with chéeſe: yet none of them all but doe live by their virtuals, every man hath his fancy, &amp; every woman will follow her own mind, and therefore though ſhe find not an Alderman or a Doctor for her diet yet ſhe may think <hi rend="roman">William</hi> her man a fit morſell for her own tooth. <hi rend="roman">I</hi> wis quoth <hi rend="roman">William,</hi> thy reaſons are goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi rend="roman">I</hi> have advantage aboue all other ſuters to follow my ſute, being in the houſe daily with her, and every evening when they are away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide ſhe hath appointed me this after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oone to come to her Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, that <hi rend="roman">I</hi> may ſhew her my reckoning and accounts &amp; in what ſort her ſtate ſtandeth: wherefore ſéeing <hi rend="roman">I</hi> have ſuch occaſion, I will no longer trifle out the time: but ſo ſoon as that buſineſſe is ended, put my ſelfe to the hazard of my happy fortune: wherefore good <hi rend="roman">Francis</hi> farewell till <hi rend="roman">I</hi> ſée thée againe, &amp; how <hi rend="roman">I</hi> ſpéed, at our next méeting thou ſhalt know. The time at laſt being come that Miſtris <hi rend="roman">Farmer</hi> had appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o have her books caſt over get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into her cloſet ſhee whiſtled for her Maid, &amp; bad her call up <hi rend="roman">William,</hi> &amp; quoth ſhe let him bring his books of account with him: the maid did as her Miſtris commanded, &amp; up comes <hi rend="roman">William</hi> with his books under his armes: &amp; after he had very reuerently don his duty to his Miſtris, ſhe had him ſit downe ſaying, now <hi rend="roman">William</hi> let me ſée theſe reckonings juſtly caſt up, for it is long ſince <hi rend="roman">I</hi> have caſt an eye into mine eſtate. Miſtris quoth he, doubt not but your eſtate is good, and your accounts juſtly kept for I have had as great regard thereto as the goods had béen my owne.
<pb facs="tcp:177918:36"/> Therein quoth ſhe I am the more beholding to thée, neither ſhal thy true ſervice goe unrewarded if I live; or if I dye thou ſhalt not be altogether forgotten.</p>
            <p>Theſe kind ſpéeches greatly comforted <hi rend="roman">Williams</hi> heart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he fell to his reckonings roundly, till his mind running too much on his Miſtris beauty, ſometimes he would miſſe and count thrée-ſcore, and foure-ſcore, nine-ſcore: Nay there you faile quoth his Miſtris, and over-fell forty, for thrée and foure is but ſeaven, tis true indéed Miſtris (ſaid he) and thrée times ſeaven is iuſt five and twenty: I tell thée quoth ſhe, tis buton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and twenty, what fellow begin you to do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in your yong yeares?</p>
            <p>O my déere Miſtris ſaid he blame me not if I doe ſo, ſéeing your ſwéet preſence hath made farre wiſer then my ſelf to do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: O my good Miſtris pardon my preſumption, for being thus bold to unburden my hearts griefe unto you, my hearty love to your ſwéet ſelfe is ſo great, that except you vouchſafe favourably to cenſure, and kindly to judge thereof, that the ſorrowes of my mind will wound my very ſoule, and make my life lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thſome unto me.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my good Miſtris, deſpiſe not your poore ſervant, but yéeld unto him ſuch ſuccour, as may prolong his dayes with many bleſſed houres.</p>
            <p>His Miſtris obſcuring her beauty with lowring browes, (like foggy vapours that blot the sky) made him this anſwer: How now Sirra, hath my too much mildneſſe made you thus ſaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y? can you ſet your love at no lower a pitch, but you muſt mount to be Maſter of your Miſtris?</p>
            <p>No Miſtris quoth he, no maſter, but your ſervant for ever. Goe to, leave your prating quoth ſhe, or I will breake thy head I ſweare, have I refuſed as thou ſéeſt, a graue and wealthy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman that might make me a Miſtris of worſhip and digni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and denied maſter Doctor of his requeſt, who as thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oweſt is at this day eſtéemed the cunningeſt Phyſition in <hi rend="roman">London,</hi> and diverſe other honeſt and well landed Gentlemen, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt young Maſter <hi rend="roman">Nevell,</hi> whoas ſome ſay is decſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of a noble houſe, and whoſe love I dare ſweare is to me moſt firmely devoted ſo that in my heart I am perſwaded he
<pb facs="tcp:177918:37"/> loves the ground the better that I tread on: &amp; ſhould I, (I ſay) forſake all theſe to make my foot my head, and my ſeruant my ſuperiour to marry thée which art a Prentice boy?</p>
            <p>Nay Sir quoth ſhe, ſéeing you are grown ſo luſty, tis time to tame you and looke to your ſteps: therefore I charge you leave the ſhop and get you into the kitchin to help the Maid ſo waſhe the diſhes and ſcowre the Ketiles; and whereas ſince my hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands deceaſe I have given foure nobles a yeare to a water bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, I will make thée ſaue me that charges, for it is well ſéene, that too long the water Tankard hath béene kept from thy lazy ſhoulders, and if thou ſcorneſt to doe this, get where thou wilt; but if thou wilt remaine with me, ſo long as thou haſt a day to ſerve, thou ſhalt be thus imployed.</p>
            <p>Hereupon ſhe called up her man <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> to ſupplie his place, and to be fore-man of the ſhop, gracing him with the keyes of the counting houſe: which <hi rend="roman">William</hi> ſéeing, ſadly went out of her ſight, wofully to himſelfe bewayling his hard fortune, but yet ſuch was his love to his Miſtris, that he rather choſe to be drudge in her kitchin, then to change her ſervice for any other. All the ſervants in the houſe much muſed at this alteration: but to no creature did his Miſtris tell the cauſe thereof, but kept it ſecret to her ſelfe: toward the evening, foorth he muſt néeds goe for water, at what time he wanted no flouts of all his fellows, nor of many of the neighbors ſervants: where méeting with his friend <hi rend="roman">Francis,</hi> diſcourſed to him the whole cauſe of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace: he greatly chaſing thereat, perſwaded him never to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſuch baſe drudgery, but rather to ſéeke preferment in ſome other place.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding <hi rend="roman">William</hi> would not follow his counſell, but rather choſe patiently to abide all brunts night being come, and ſupper ended, <hi rend="roman">William</hi> was ſet to performe his penance for his preſumption in love, that is to ſay, to ſcrape the trenchers, ſcowre the kettles and ſpits, and to waſh up the diſhes: which he went about with ſuch good will, that it ſéemed to him rather a pleaſure then a paine.</p>
            <p>His Miſtris cloſſet joyning to the kitchin, had a ſecret place therein to look into the kitchin, were cloſely ſitting, ſhe earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:177918:37"/> beheld her man how he beſtirred himſelfe in his buſines: Whereupon ſhe entered into this conſideration with her ſelfe. Now fle for ſhame, how Ill doth it beſéeme me to ſet ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome a youth to ſuch drudgery? if he bore a mans mind he would never indure it, but being of a baſe and ſervile condition, he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſily indure the yoake of ſervitude, and yet I am too blame ſo to thinke, for if he had ſtubbornly diſobeyed my commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment how could I otherwiſe judge, but that in pride and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine he thought himſelfe too good to be at any direction: ſome ſervants would in ſuch a caſe have given me many foule words, and rather malepartly ſet me at nought, and forſake my ſervice, then to have indured the tearms of diſgrace that he hath done by this means: but héereby it is evident that love thinks nothing too much. Well <hi rend="roman">Will</hi> quoth ſhe; the vertue of thy mind ſhall bréed better thoughts in thy Miſtris, which ſhall make her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thy good will in a large meaſure: ſée ſée how neately he goes through his work, how handſomely he handles every thing: and ſurely well may I ſuppoſe that he which is ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a ſervant, would certainly prove a kind husband, for this hath béene no ſlender triall of his conſtant heart. With that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Maid and ſome other of the ſervants talke with him, ſhe lending a héedfull eare to their ſpéech, heard them ſpeake to this purpoſe: good Lord <hi rend="roman">William</hi> quoth one, I maruell much that you being of ſo good parents and having ſo little a while to ſerve, will be thus vſed at her hands? it were too much if you were but this day bound prentice, to be ſet to ſuch ſlavery: I ſweare quoth an oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, I have thrée times longer to ſerve then you and if ſhe ſhould bid me doe as thou doſt, I would bid her doe it herſelfe with a morin: Ile tell you what quoth the third, Ile be plaine and vſe but few words, but I would ſée my faire Miſtris with the black Devill before I would doe it.</p>
            <p>Well we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l my maſters quoth <hi rend="roman">William,</hi> you are mad merry wags but I take it as great favour done me by my Miſtris thus to imploy me, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eby I might have knowledge how to decke up a kitchen that méeting with a bad huswife to my wife I know how to inſtruct her in houſhold affaires: I care for no ſuch favour ſaid he.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:38"/>
            <p>Their Miſtris hearing all, ſaid nothing, but determined to try them all what they would doe ere it were long: wherefore being now greatly affectioned to her man, couered her love with ſuch diſcretion, that none could perceive it. For Maſter Doctor being newly returned, came thither puffing and blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaying, he was never ſo ſerved ſince he was borne; quoth he, ſince I was here, I have at leaſt ridden an hundred miles with an arrant knave that carried me I knew not whether: he rode with me out of Biſhops-gate foorth right as far as <hi rend="roman">Ware,</hi> and then compaſſing all <hi rend="roman">Suffolke,</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Norfolke,</hi> he brought me backe againe through <hi rend="roman">Eſſex,</hi> and ſo conducted me to Black-wall in Middleſex to ſéeke out my Lady <hi rend="roman">Swinborne,</hi> my good Lady and Miſtris: at laſt I ſaw it was no ſuch matter, but the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine being diſpoſed to mocke me, brought me to a woman Egiptian, as blacke as the great Divell, who lay in child-bed and was but delivered of a child of her owne colour: to the which in deſpite of my heard they made me be God-father, where it coſt me thrée crownes, and I was glad I ſo eſcaped, and who was the author of all this deceipt but Maſter <hi rend="roman">Nevell?</hi> but if ever I come to give him Phiſicke, if I make him not have the ſquirt for five dayes, count me the verieſt dunce that ever wore veluet cap.</p>
            <p>Maſter Doctor quoth ſhe, I am very ſorie you were ſo vſed, notwithſtanding to make Maſter <hi rend="roman">Nevell</hi> and you friends <hi rend="roman">I</hi> will beſtow a breakefaſt upon you to morrow, if it pleaſe you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my offer. Faire Widdow quoth he, never a one in the world would have vrged me to be friends with him but your ſelfe, and I am contented for your ſake to doe it: and thus till next morning he took his leave.</p>
            <p>Next day as ſoone as ſhe was up ſhe called up one of her men ſaying, Sirra run quickly, take a baſket and fetch me a buſhel of oyſters from Billinſgate; the fellow frowning ſaid, I pray you ſend another, for I am buſie in the ſhop.</p>
            <p>Why knade quoth ſhe, Ile have thée goe, quoth he, make a drudge of ſome other and not of me, for to be plaine I will not goe. No quoth ſhe, call me <hi rend="roman">Richard</hi> hither: when he came, ſhe deſired him very gently to fetch her a buſhel of oyſters.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:38"/>
            <p>Why Miſtreſſe quoth he, my friends ſet me not here to be a Porter to fetch Oiſters from Billingſgate. I tell you true, I ſcorne you ſhould require any ſuch matter of me. Is it true quoth ſhe? very well, I will remember this when you forget it. Thus when ſhe had tried them all, ſhe called her man <hi rend="roman">William,</hi> ſaying: ſirra goodman ſcullian take the great cloſe baſket, and fetch me a buſhell of oyſters from Billinſgate, &amp; look you tarry not. I will forſooth Miſtris quoth he, &amp; preſently away he went with ſuch good will as none could go with better, being marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous glad that ſhe would requeſt any thing at his hands.</p>
            <p>When he was come againe, with a ſmiling countenance ſhe ſaid, what Wilkin art thou come already? it is well done, I pray thée bring ſome of them up into my Cloſſet, that I may taſte how good they be: yes forſooth quoth William, and after her he went, the Maide likewiſe carried up a couple of white manchets, and with a Diaper napkin covered the table. Now Maid quoth ſhe, fetch me a pint of the beſt red wine: I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth ſaid the Maid.</p>
            <p>Miſtris ſaid William, if it pleaſe you, I will open your Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for you; I pray you do quoth ſhe: then taking a towell on his arme, and a knife in his hand, being glad he had gotten ſo good an office, ſhewed himſelfe ſo feat and expert in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he opened as faſt as his Miſtreſſe could eat.</p>
            <p>Beléeve me William quoth ſhe, you are nimble at an oyſter, and quick in carving up ſhell fiſh, though dull in caſting up ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, I pray thee tell me how many ſhels are in three and thirtie oyſters? Thréeſcore and ſix ſaid William: you are a witty youth quoth ſhe, if thy ſpéech be true it muſt then néeds follow that I have eaten thrée and thirty oyſters, have alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured thréeſcore and ſix ſhels, which is too much for one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans breakfaſt in a cold morning in conſcience, and therefore I had néed quickly to give over, leaſt I break my belly with oyſter ſhels: whereupon ſhe cald her maid, ſaying: come hither <hi rend="roman">Ioane,</hi> and bring me a goblet of wine that I may waſh Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams ſhels from my ſtomack.</p>
            <p>Indéed Miſtris quoth he, if you take my words ſo, I ſpoke without book: it is true quoth ſhe, for they are alwaies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:177918:39"/> that are never within, and either thy knowledge is ſmall, or thy blindneſſe great, or oyſter ſhels very ſoft, that I ſhould eat ſo many and never féele one: for ſurely, if there be thrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ſix oyſter ſhels in thrée and thirty oyſters, there muſt néeds be as many more in three and thirty oyſters: and to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme my words true, behold here the ſhels that were out of the oyſters, now ſhew me thoſe that were within the oyſters. William ſeeing his Miſtris thus pleaſant, began to gather ſome courage to himſelfe, and therefore thus uttered his mind: Deare Miſtris, néeds muſt I prove both blinde in ſight, and dull in conceipt, while your faire eyes that gives light to the Sunne obſcure themſelves, and dark the glory of their ſhine, when I ſéek to receive comfort thereby: and the want of your good will makes my wits ſo weak, that like a barren trée it yéelds no fruit at all.</p>
            <p>True quoth ſhe: thrée times ſeven is iuſt five and twenty: but tell me what is the cauſe that moves thée to deſire my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and to requeſt my good will? Good Miſtris pardon me quoth he, and I will tell you: whereupon ſhe replied, ſaying, truſt me William, my pardon is eaſier to be gotten then the Popes, and therefore be not afraid to procéed. Why then my deare Miſtris, ſéeing you have ſo graciouſly granted liberty to my hearts advocate, to pleade at the bar of your beauty, and to open the bill of my complaint: know this, that hope againſt hope perſwaded me to labour for your love, that gaining the ſame I might be called a bleſſed man by winning ſuch a wife.</p>
            <p>What <hi rend="roman">Will</hi> quoth ſhe, art thou not aſhamed, that ſuch a youth as thy ſelfe, a lad, a ſtripling, a prentice boy, ſhould in the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of his age, cumber himſelfe with the cares of the world, and wantonly take a wife, that knowes not how to guide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? I tell thée fellow, firſt learne to thrive, and then wive. O my deare Miſtris, ſaid William, let not pleaſant youth which is the glory of many be a diſgrace to me: neither with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out triall déere Miſtris diſable not my manhood, which now I take to be in his chiefe prime.</p>
            <p>Nay quoth ſhe, if thou wilt have thy manhood tried, prepare thy ſelfe for the warres, and purchaſe honour by beating down
<pb facs="tcp:177918:39"/> our countries foes, and ſo ſhalt thou weare the golden wreath of honour for ever. In troth Miſtris quoth he, I had rather have my manhood tried in another place. Y faith where quoth ſhee? by my troth ſaid he, in your ſoft bed, which is far better then the hard field: why thou bold knave quoth ſhe, it were a good déed to make you a bird of Bridewell, for your ſaucineſſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeve me Miſtris quoth he, I am ſorie you ſhould be offended, rather will I get me into a corner and die through diſdaine, then ſtay in your ſight and grieve you? and with that away he went. She ſéeing him ſo haſtily depart, called him againe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: William come hither, turne againe you faint hearted coward, what art thou afraid of Bridewell? uſe thy ſelfe well, and I will be thy friend: the young man that with theſe words was revived like a ſick man out of a dead ſound, turning mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to his Miſtris, gave her a kiſſe, ſaying: on that condition I give you this. How now ſir quoth ſhe, I called you not back to be ſo bold: in good ſadneſſe do ſo againe, and I will give you on the eare.</p>
            <p>Nay Miſtris quoth he, if that be all the danger, take then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and lay me on the eare (ſo I may lay you on the lips) and ſpare not: nay then ſaid his Miſtris, I ſée my too much ſoftneſſe makes thée ſaucy, therefore for feare thou ſhouldeſt catch a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet, I charge thée on paine of loves diſpleaſure, to get you downe about your buſineſſe, and ſée that all things be in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt my friends come: why goe you not? what ſtand you in a maze? pack I ſay and be gone.</p>
            <p>And thus my deare Miſtris quoth he, parts my ſoule out of Paradiſe, and my heart from heavens ioy: notwithſtanding you command and I conſent and alwayes let me finde favour, as I am forward to follow your precepts, and therewithall away he went.</p>
            <p>He was no ſooner gone, but ſhe having determined what to do, ſent for her friends, at what time the Alderman comming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Maſter Doctor, ſhe had alſo invited Maſter Peachie and his Wife, and with them came gallant young Nevill.</p>
            <p>When they were all ſet at the table, after they had well taſted of the delicates there prepared: Miſtris Farmer told them for
<pb facs="tcp:177918:40"/> two cauſes ſhe had requeſted their companie that day to break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt: the one was, that maſter Doctor and young Nevill might be made friends: and the other that in their ſight ſhe might make her ſelfe ſure to her husband, that they might be witnes of their vowes.</p>
            <p>The companie ſaid, they ſhould be very glad to ſée ſo good a work performed: whereupon ſhee calling up all her men ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſpake to this purpoſe. My good friends and kinde neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, becauſe I will have none ignorant, of that which is to be effected, I have preſumed to bring my ſervants into your preſence, that they alſo may beare record of the reconciliation betwixt Maſter Doctor and Maſter Nevill, and therefore my Maſters, if your hearts conſent to an unitie, declare it by ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hands, that it may not bee ſaid, that my houſe was the bréeder of brawles, and on that condition I drink to you both: the Gentlemen both pledged her, and according to her requeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded the quarrell.</p>
            <p>When this was done, ſhe merrily told them, that among her men ſhe had choſen her Maſter: albeit quoth ſhe, this matter may ſéeme ſtrange in your ſight, and my fancie too much ruled by follie, yet this my determination I purpoſe by Gods grace to follow, hoping it ſhall bréed no offence to any in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, in ſuch a chance to make mine own choice.</p>
            <p>Her man Richard, &amp; the reſt that ſuppoſed themſelves moſt graced by her favours, began at this ſpéech to look ſomething peart, and all the companie held opinion that ſhe bore the beſt minde to the foreman of her Shop: for firſt of all turning her ſpeech to him, ſhe ſaid: Richard come hither, thou haſt greatly to praiſe God for making thée ſo proper a man, thou art a neat fellow, and haſt excellent qualities, for thou art not proud, nor high minded, but haſt a care to thy buſineſſe, and to kéepe the Shop: and becauſe I have committed great matters into thy hands, I pray thée go downe and look to thy charge, for I have nothing more to ſay to thée at this time.</p>
            <p>The fellow at theſe words lookt as blew under the eyes, as a ſtale Codſhead under the gill: and going downe the ſtaires ſhook his head like one that had a flea in his eare.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:40"/>
            <p>Now come hither Iohn quoth ſhe, I muſt néeds ſay thou art come of good parents, &amp; thou knowſt they bound thee not Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to fetch oyſters from Billinſgate like a Porter, nor to have thy daintie fingers ſet to drudgerie, therefore good Iohn get you downe after your fellow, for here is nothing for you to doe at this time.</p>
            <p>Her man William, that all this while was playing the ſcul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in the kitchin was then ſent for, who comming before the companie with his face all begrim'd, and his cloathes all grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, his Miſtris ſpake in this manner. What a ſlovenlie knave comes here? were not this a fit man think ye to be Maſter of this houſe and Lord of my love?</p>
            <p>Now by my troth ſaid Miſtris <hi rend="roman">Peachie,</hi> I never ſaw a more unhandſome fellow in my life: f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e how hee ſtinkes of kitchin ſtuffe: what a face and neck hath he? a bodie might ſet Léekes in the very durt of his lips. I thinke in my conſcience thrée pound of Sope, &amp; a barrell of Water is little enough to ſcowre him cleane: the like flowts uſed all the reſt at poore William, to which his Miſtris made this anſwer.</p>
            <p>Good Lord my maſters, how much do your ſights deceive you? in my ſight he looks the lovelieſt of them all, having a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant countenance, and a good grace, and ſo pleaſing is he in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part to my ſight, that ſurely if hee will accept of mee for his wife, I will not refuſe him for my husband: her friends look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one upon another, and marvelling at her ſpéech, thought verily ſhe had but ieſted, till ſuch time ſhe took him by the hand, and gave him a kiſſe.</p>
            <p>Whereupon William ſpake thus unto her: faire Miſtris, ſéeing it hath pleaſed you, beyond my deſert, and contrarie to my expectation to make me ſo gracious an offer, worthie I were to live a beggar, if I ſhould refuſe ſuch a treaſure: and thereupon I give you my heart and my hand: and I receive it quoth ſhe, for it is thy vertue and true humilitie that hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered my former conceipts, for few men would have wonne a wife as thou didſt. No, how did he win you ſaid Harris Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill? by fetching oyſters from Billingſgate quoth ſhe, which I know you would not have done, ſéeing all the reſt of my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb facs="tcp:177918:41"/> ſcorn'd to do it at my requeſt: Sblood quoth Harrie, by feching of oyſters: I would have fetch oyſters, and muſtles, and cockles too, to have got ſo good a bargaine.</p>
            <p>The Alderman and the Doctor lookt ſtrangely at this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: nevertheleſſe ſéeing it was not to be helpt, they commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her choice, ſaying: it was better for a man in ſuch a caſe, to be favourable in a womans eyes, then to have much gold in his coffers. Then did ſhe ſet her black man by her white ſide, and calling the reſt of her ſervants (in the ſight of her friends) ſhe made them do reverence unto him, whom they for his drudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſcorned ſo much before: ſo the breakfaſt ended, ſhe wild them a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l next morning, to beare him companie to Church, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which time, William was ſo daintily tricht up, that all thoſe which beheld him, confeſt he was a moſt comely, trim, and proper man, and after they were married, they lived long together in ioy and proſperous eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Harrie Nevill</hi> became ſo grieved hereat, that ſoone after he went from Maſter Peachie, and dwelt with a Goldſmith, and when he had beene a while there, committing a fault with his Maſters daughter, he departed thence and became a Barber-Surgion: but there his Miſtris and he were ſo familiar, that it nothing pleaſed his Maſter, ſo that in halfe a yeare he ſought a new ſervice and became a Cook: and then a Comfetmaker dwelling with maſter Baltazar, where after he grew ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing cunning, having done ſome ſhrewd turne in that place, he forſooke that ſervice: and became a Smith, where their maide <hi rend="roman">Iudeth</hi> fell ſo highly in love with him that he for pure good will which he bore her, ſhewed his Maſter a faire paire of heeles: and then practiſed to be a Ioyner, where he continued till hee heard his Father was ſick, who for his abominable ſwearing had caſt him from his favour, but after he had long miſt him, and that he could heare no tidings of his untoward and wilde wanton Sonne, hee ſent into divers places to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire for him, and at laſt one of this ſervants lighed where he was, by which meanes he came to his father againe: who in a few yeares after, leaving his life, this ſonne <hi rend="roman">Harrie</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Lord of all his lands: and comming upon a day to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb facs="tcp:177918:41"/> with his men waiting upon him, he cauſed a great dinner to be prepared, and ſent for all thoſe that had béen his maſters and miſtreſſes: who being come, he thus began to commune with them My good friends, I underſtand that a certaine kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of mine was ſometimes your ſervant, and as I take it, his name was <hi rend="roman">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrie N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll:</hi> who as I heare, uſed himſelfe but homely toward you, being a very wilde and ungracious fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the report whereof hath béene ſome griefe to me, being one that alwayes wiſht him well: wherefore look what dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage he hath done you I pray you tell me, and I am content with reaſon to ſée you ſatisfied, ſo that he may have your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to be made a fréeman.</p>
            <p>Surely ſir ſaid <hi rend="roman">Peachie</hi> for mine own part I can ſay little, ſave only that he was ſo full of love, that he would ſeldome fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his buſineſſe at his occupation: but that matter I fréely forgive and will not be his hindrance in any thing. Marry ſir ſaid the Goldſmith, I cannot ſay to: for truly ſir he plaid the théefe in my houſe, robbing my daughter of her maidenhead, which he nor you is ever able to recompence, though you gave me a thouſand pound, yet I thank God ſhe is married and doth well, I am the glader of that ſaid the Gentleman, and for that fault I will give toward her maintenance forty pound.</p>
            <p>The Barber hearing him ſay ſo, told him that hee had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured him as much, and had beene more bold a great deale then became him, whereby (quoth he) I was made a ſcorne among my neighbours. Tuſh you ſpeake of ill will ſaid the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, if your wife will ſay ſo I will beléeve it: to which words the woman made this anſwer. Good ſir, will you beléeve me there was never ſo much matter, the youth was an honeſt faire conditioned young man, but my huſband bearing a naughty iealous minde, grew ſuſpicious without cauſe, onely becauſe he ſaw that his ſervant was kinde and gentle unto me, and would have done any thing that I requeſted: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I have had many a fowle word for his ſake, and carried ſome bitter blowes too, but all is one, I am not the firſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that hath ſuffered iniury without cauſe: alas good ſoule ſaid the Gentleman, I am right ſorry for thy griefe, and
<pb facs="tcp:177918:42"/> to make thée amende. I will beſtow on thée twentie Angels, ſo your husband will not take it in dudgin; the woman with a low curſte gave him thanks, ſaying: truly ſir I am highly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to you, and truly I ſhall love you the better becauſe you are ſo like him. The ſmith likewiſe for his maide ſaid all that he might, to whoſe marriage the Gentleman gave twentie pound: thus after hee had fully ended with them all, hee made himſelfe knowne unto them, at what time they all reioyced g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eatly, and then after he had beſtowed on them a ſumptuous dinner, they all departed. And ever after, this Gentleman kept men of all theſe occupations in his own houſe, himſelf being as good a workman as any of them all.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. X. Of the greene king of S. Martins and his merry feats.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here dwelt in S. Martins a iollie Shooema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, hee was commonly called the Gréene king, for that upon a time he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before King <hi rend="roman">Henry,</hi> with all his men cloathed in gréene, he himſelfe being ſuted all in gréene Satten. He was a man very humorous, of ſmall ſtature, but moſt cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, and continually he uſed the Fencing: ſchoole when he went abroad, he carried alwayes a two handed ſword on his ſhoulder, or under his arme: he kept continually thirtie or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſervants, and kept in his houſe moſt bountifull fare: you ſhall underſtand that in his young yeares, his father dying, left him a good portion, ſo that he was in great credit and eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among his neighbours, and that which made him more happie, was this, that God bleſt him with the gift of a good wife, who was a very comely young woman, and therewithall very carefull for his commoditie: but he whoſe minde was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together of merriment, little reſpected his profit in regard of his pleaſure: inſomuch that through his waſtefull expence he brought povertie upon himſelfe ere he was aware, ſo that he could not do as he was accuſtomed: which when his daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions
<pb facs="tcp:177918:42"/> perceived, they by little and little ſhund his company, and if at any time he paſſed by them, perhaps they would lend him a nod, or give him a good morrow and make no more a doe.</p>
            <p>And is it true quoth the Gréene king, doth want of money part good company, or is my countenance chaunged, that they do not know me? I have ſéene the day when neuer a knave of them all, but would have made much of my dog for my ſake, and have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me twenty ſalutations on a Sunday morning, for one poore pint of Muſkadine: and what, hath a throd bare cloake ſcarde all good fellowſhip? why though I have not my wonted habites, I have ſtill the ſame heart: and though my money be gone, my mind is not altred: why then what Iacks are they to reject mée? I, I, now I finde my wives tale true, for then ſhe was wont to ſay, Husband, husband, refraine theſe trencher flies, theſe ſmooth faced flatterers, that like drones live upon the hony of your labour and ſucke away the ſwéetnes of your ſubſtance. I wis, I wis, if once you ſhould come in want, there is not the beſt of them all, that would truſt you for tengroates: by which ſaying Ile lay my life ſhe is a witch, for it is come as juſt to pas as Marlins prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. I would the other day but have borrowed 12 d. &amp; I tride 13 f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inds, &amp; went without it: it being ſo, let them go hang themſelvs for I wil into Flanders, that is flat, and leave theſe ſlaves to their ſervill conditions, where I will try if a firkin barrell of butter bée worth a pot of ſtrong béere, and a loade of Holland chéeſe, better then a gallon of Charnico: and if it be by the croſſe of this ſword I will neuer ſtaine my credit with ſuch a baſe commodity againe.</p>
            <p>With that he went to his wife, ſaying: woman doſt thou heare? I pray thée looke well to thy buſines till I come againe: for why? to drive away melancholy, I am minded to walke a mile or twaine: but huſband quoth ſhe, were you there where you layd your plate to pawne? I pray you is it not miſuſed? and is it ſafe? wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an quoth he I was there, and it is ſafe I warrant thée, for euer comming into thy hands againe, thou knoweſt I borrowed but twentie marke on it, and they have ſold it for twentie pound: tis gone wife, tis gone. O hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>band quoth ſhe, what hard fortune have we to be ſo ill delt withall? and therewithall ſhe wept, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e quoth he leave thy wéeping, hang it up, let it goe, the beſt is, it
<pb facs="tcp:177918:43"/> neuer coſt us groate: were our friends living that gave us that, they would give us more: but in vaine it is to mourn for a matter that cannot be helpt, farewell wife, looke to thy houſe, and let the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s plie their worke. The gréene king having thus taken his l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave, went toward Billingſ-gate, of purpoſe to take Barge: w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere by the way hée met with <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> now now the firkin Fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Finchlane: What maſter quoth he, well met, I pray whith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r are you walking? a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> how doe all our friends in ſaint Martins? Will you not have a craſh ere you goe?</p>
            <p>Y faith <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> quoth he, thou knoweſt I am a good fellow, and one that hath not béen a niggard to thée at any time, therefore if thou wilt beſtow any muſick on me doe, and if it pleaſe God that I return ſafely from <hi rend="roman">Flanders</hi> againe, I will pay thée well for thy paines; but now I have no money for muſick: Gods-nigs quoth <hi rend="roman">Anthony,</hi> whether you have money or no, you ſhall have mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, I doe not allways requeſt coyne of my feiends for my cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: what, you are not euery body, and ſéeing you are going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond ſea, I will beſtow a pinte of wine on you at the Salutation: ſaiſt thou ſo <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> quoth he, in good ſooth I will not refuſe thy curteſie, and with that they ſtept into the Tauern, where <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> cald for wine: and drawing forth his Fiddle began to play, and after he had ſcrapte halfe a ſcore leſſons he began to ſing.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" rend="roman" type="song">
               <body>
                  <l>When ſhould a man ſhew himſelfe gentle and kinde,</l>
                  <l>When ſhould a man comfort the ſorrowfull minde?</l>
                  <l>O Anthony now, now, now.</l>
                  <l>O Anthony now, now, now.</l>
                  <l>When is the beſt time to drinke with a friend?</l>
                  <l>When is it meeteſt my money to ſpend?</l>
                  <l>O Anthony now, now, now.</l>
                  <l>O Anthony now, now, now.</l>
                  <l>When goes the King of good fellowes away?</l>
                  <l>That ſo much delighted in dauncing and play?</l>
                  <l>O Anthony now, now, now.</l>
                  <l>O Anthony now, now, now.</l>
                  <l>And when ſhould I bid my Maſter farewell?</l>
                  <l>Whoſe bountie and curteſie ſo did excell?</l>
                  <l>O Anthony now, now, now.</l>
                  <l>O Anthony now, now, now.</l>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:43"/>
            <p>Loe ye now Maſter quoth he, this ſong have I made for your ſake, and by the grace of God when you are gone I will ſing it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sunday morning vnder your wives window, that ſhe may know we dranke together ere you parted: I pray thée do ſo ſaid the Gréene king, and do my commendations vnto her, and tell her at my returne I hope to make merry.</p>
            <p>Thus after they had made an end of their wine, and paid for the ſhot, <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> putting up his Fiddle departed ſeeking to change muſicke for money: while the Gréene king of Saint Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins ſailed in Graveſend Barge. But <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> in his abſence ſung this ſong ſo often in Saint Martins, that thereby he purchaſt a name which he neuer loſt till his dying day, for euer after men called him nothing but <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> now now.</p>
            <p>But it is to be remembred that the Gréen kings wife became ſo carefull in her buſineſſe, and governed her ſelfe with ſuch wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in all her affaires, that during her husbands abſence ſhe did not onely pay many of his debts, but alſo got into her houſe every thing that was neceſſary to be had, the which her diligence won ſuch commendations, that her credit in all places was verie good, and her gaines (through Gods bleſſing) came ſo flowing in, that before her husband came home, ſhe was had in good reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with her neighbours: and having no néed of any of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, every one was ready to proffer her curteſie, ſaying good neighbour if you want any thing tell us, and looke what friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we may doe you, be ſure you ſhall find it.</p>
            <p>I neighbour quoth ſhe, I know your kindneſſe, and may ſpeake thereof by experience: well may I compare you to him that would never bid any man to dinner, but at two of the clocke in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noone, when he was aſſured they had fild their bellies before, and that they would not touch his meate, except for manners ſake: wherefore for my part I will give you thankes, when I take be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of your proffer.</p>
            <p>Why neighbour we ſpeake for good will quoth they: Tis true quoth ſhée, and ſo ſay they that call for a freſh quart to beſtow on a drunken man, when they know it would doe him as much good in his bootes as in his belly.</p>
            <p>Well neighbour quoth they, God be thanked that you have no
<pb facs="tcp:177918:44"/> cauſe to uſe friends: Mary Amen quoth ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, for if I had I think I ſhould finde few here, There and the like greetings were often betwixt her and her neighbors.</p>
            <p>Til at laſt her husband came home, &amp; to his great comfort found his eſtate ſo good, that he had great cauſe to praiſe God for the ſame, for a warme purſe is the beſt medicine for a cold heart that may be. The gréene king therefore bearing himſelfe as brave as ever he did, having ſworne himſelfe a faithfull companion to his two hand-ſworde, would never goe without it.</p>
            <p>Now when his auncient acquaintance law him again ſo gallant, every one was ready to curry favour with him, and many would proffer him the wine. And where before they were wont ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to thruſt him next the kennell, and nothing to reſpect his povert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, they gave him now the upper hand in every place, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting him with cap and knée: but he remembring how ſleightly they ſet by him in his néede, did now as ſleightly eſtéeme their flattery, ſaying: I cry you mercy, me thinkes I have ſéene your face but I never knew you for my friend. No quoth one, I dwell at Alderſgate, and am your néere neighbor, and ſo much the worſe ſaid the Gréene king: wherefore quoth the other? Becauſe ſaid he, I thinke the place méete for an honeſter man. I truſt ſir ſaid his neighbour, you know no hurt by me.</p>
            <p>Nor any goodnes quoth the gréene king, but I remember you are he, or one of them of whom once I would have borrowed fortie pence, yet could not get it, if thereby I might have ſaved fifty lives: therefore goodman hog, goodman cog, or goodman dog, chuſe you which, ſcrape no acquaintance of me, nor come any more in my company, I would adviſe you, leaſt with my long ſword I crop your cowards legs, and make you ſtand like Saint Martins begger upon two ſtilts. The fellow hearing him ſay ſo, went his wayes, and never durſt ſpeake to him afterward.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" rend="blackletterType" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:44"/>
            <head>Chap. 11. How the Greene King went a walking with his wife, and got Anthony now now to play before them, in which ſort hee went with her to Briſtow.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Gréen king being a man that was much given to goe abroad, his wife upon a time, thus made her mone to him: good Lord husband quoth ſhe, I thinke you are the unkindeſt man alive, for as often as you walke abroad, you were neuer the man that would take me in your company: it is no ſmall griefe to me, while I ſit doating at home, every Sunday and Holy-day, to ſée how kindely other men walke with their wives, and lovingly beare them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany into the fields, that thereby they may have ſome recreation after their wéekes weary toyle: this pleaſure haue they for their paines, but I poore ſoule could never get ſuch curteſie at your hands: either it muſt néeds be that you love me but little, or elſe you are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hamed of my company, and I tell you true you have no reaſon either for the one or the other. Certainly wife ſaid hée, I ſhould be ſorrie to drive any ſuch conceit into thy head, but ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you find your ſelfe grieved in this kinde, let me intreate thée to be content, and when thou ſhalt perceive that my love is not ſmall toward thée, nor my liking ſo bad to be aſhamed to have thée goe by my ſide, Thurſday next is Saint Iames day, againſt which time prepare thy ſelfe to goe with me to the faire, where by the grace of God Ile beſtow a fat Pig upon thée, and there I meane to be merry: and doubt not but I will walke with thee till thou art weary of walking. Nay quoth ſhee, I ſhould never be weary of your company, though I went with you to the Worlds end: God a mercy for that wife quoth hée, but ſo doing I doubt I ſhould trie you a very good foote-woman, or a bad flatterer.</p>
            <p>Thus it paſt till Thurſday came, in the meane ſeaſon méeting with two or thrée other ſhoomakers, he asked them if they would walke with him and his wife to Saint Iames faire: That wee will with all our hearts: but will you not like flinchers flie from your words quoth he? To that (they ſaid) if they did they would forfeit a gallon of wine.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:45"/>
            <p>Tuſh ſaid the gréene king, talke not ſo me of a gallon of wine, but will you bee bound in twenty pound a péece to performe it? Why what néeds bands for ſuch a matter quoth they? we truſt you will take our wordes for more then that. My maſters ſaid the greene king, the world is growne to that paſſe, that words are counted but wind, and I will truſt you as little on your word as Long Meg on her honeſty: therefore if you will not be bound, chuſe, I will make no account of your company. The men hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſay ſo, knowing him to be a man of a merry mind, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their wits were all waſht with wine, to the Scriveners they went, and bound themſelves in twenty pound according to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
            <p>They had no ſooner made an end of this merry match, but as they ſtumbled into another Taverne, who ſhould they méet but Anthony now now: who as ſoon as he ſpide the gréen King ſmiling with a wrie mouth he joyfully imbrac't him with both his hands, ſaying: what my good maſter well met, when came you from the other ſide the water? by my troth you are welcome with all my heart. God a mercy good Anthony quoth he, but how chance you come no more into Saint Martins?</p>
            <p>O Maſter quoth he, you know what a dainty commoditie I made at your parting to Graveſendbarge? Yes mary ſaid the gréene king what of that? why quoth he by ſinging it under your window, all the merry ſhoomakers in Saint Martins tooke it by the toe: and now they have made it even as common as a printed Ballad, and I have gotten ſuch a name by it, that now I am cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led nothing but Anthony now now.</p>
            <p>Why Maſter ile tell you, it hath made me as well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Cheapeſide, as the cat in the creame pan: for as ſoone as the Goldeſmiths wives ſpie mée, and as I paſſe along by the Marchants daughters, the apes will laugh at me as paſſes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that all the little boyes in the ſtréets will run after mée like a ſort of Emits. Anthony now now ſayes one: Anthony now now another: good Lord, good Lord, you never knew the like: heare ye maſter? I am ſure that ſong hath gotten mée ſince you went, more pence then your wife hath pins: and ſéeing you are come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I will make the ſecond part very ſhortly.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:45"/>
            <p>But heareſt thou <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> ſaid he? if thou wilt come to me on Saint Iames his day in the Morning, thou ſhalt walke with us to the faire, for I meane to make merry with my wife that day: Maſter quoth he, by cock and pie, I will not miſſe you. And thus after they had made <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> drinke he departed.</p>
            <p>Saint Iames his day at laſt being come, he cal'd up his wife betimes, and bad her make her ready, if ſhe would to the faire: who very willingly did ſo: and in the meane ſpace her husband went to his cubbert, and tooke thereout forty faire ſoveraignes, and going ſecretly to one of his ſervants, he willed him to take good heed of his houſe, and to ſée that his fellowes plide their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for quoth he, I goe with my wife to Saint Iames faire, and perhaps you ſhall not ſée us againe this ſennight: Well Maſter ſaid the fellow, I will have regard to your buſines I warrant you. Wherewith he cal'd his wife, ſaying: come wife will you walke? with a good will husband quoth ſhe, I am ready: with that <hi rend="roman">An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> now now, began to ſcrape on his treable viall, and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a huntſup, ſaid good morrow maſter good morrow, foure a clocke and a faire morning.</p>
            <p>Well ſaid <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> quoth he, we be ready for thy company, therefore along before, and let us heare what muſicke you can make. Fie huſband quoth ſhe, take not the Fidler with you for ſhame: tuſh be content quoth he, Muſicke makes a ſad mind mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: ſo away they went, and at Saint Giles in the fields he met the reſt of his company: well found my maſters quoth he, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you have a care of your bonds: ſo away they went with the Fidler before them, &amp; the Gréene king with his two hand ſworde marching like a maſter of Fenc going to play his prize: when they came to the high way turning downe to Weſtminſter, his wife ſaid: y faith huſband we ſhall come to the faire too ſoone, for Gods ſake let us walke a little further. Content wife quoth he, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they went to Kenſington, where they brake their faſt, and had good ſport by tumbling on the gréene graſſe, where <hi rend="roman">Anthony</hi> brake his Fiddle, for which cauſe the Gréene king gave him ten ſhillings, and willed him to goe back and buy a new one.</p>
            <p>And now my friends quoth he, if you will walke with mée to Brainford I will beſtow your dinner upon you, becauſe I have a
<pb facs="tcp:177918:46"/> a minde to walke with my wife? they were content, but by that time they came there, the woman began to wax ſomewhat wearie, &amp; becauſe the day was farre ſpent before they had dined, they lay there all night: where he told his friends that the next morning he would bring his wife to ſée the George in Colebrook, and then would turne home: but to be briefe, when he came there, he told them flatly he meant to goe to Saint Iames his faire at Briſtow: for qûoth he my wife hath longed to walke with me, and I meane to give her walking-worke enough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But ſir quoth they, we meane not to goe thither: before God but you ſhall quoth hée, or forfeit your band. The men ſéeing no remedy, went along to Briſtow on foote, whereby the poore woman became ſo weary, that an hundred times ſhe wiſht ſhe had not come foorth of doores: but from that time till ſhe died, ſhe never intreated her husband to walke with her againe.</p>
            <p>An hundred merry feates more did he, which in this place is too much to be ſet downe. For afterward Tom Drum comming from the winning of Muſtleborow, came to dwell with him, where he diſcourſed all his adventures, in the wars: and according to his old cogging humor, attributed other mens deeds to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for quoth he, it was I that killed the firſt Scot in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, yet I was content to give the honour thereof to Sir Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell Muſgrave, notwithſtanding quoth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all men knowes that this hand of mine kild Tom Trotter that terrible traytor, which in deſpite of us, kept the Caſtell ſo long, &amp; at laſt as he cowardly forſooke it, and ſecretly ſought to flye, with this blade of mine I broacht him like a roaſting pigge. Moreover, Parſon Ribble had never made himſelfe ſo famous but by my meanes. Theſe were his daily vaunts, till his lies were ſo manifeſt that hée could no longer ſtand in them. But after the Greene king had long lived a gallant houſe-kéeper, at laſt being aged and blinde, he dyed, after he had done many good déedes to divers poore men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:177918:46"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
